<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The rainebow, or, A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse the tenth day of Iune, 1617 by Immanuel Bourne ...</title>
            <author>Bourne, Immanuel, 1590-1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1617</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 181 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16505</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3418</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S725</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22301576</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22301576</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25361</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16505)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25361)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1773:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The rainebow, or, A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse the tenth day of Iune, 1617 by Immanuel Bourne ...</title>
                  <author>Bourne, Immanuel, 1590-1672.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 64 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Adams,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1617.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-I⁴.</note>
                  <note>Numerous errors in paging.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Genesis IX, 13 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25361:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE RAINEBOW, <hi>OR,</hi> A SERMON PREACHED AT PAVLS CROSSE THE tenth day of Iune. 1617. By IMMANVEL BOVRNE Maſter of Artes and Preacher of Gods Word.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ECCLESIASTICVS 43.11, 12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Looke vpon the Rainebowe, and praiſe him that made it, &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Thomas Adams, featuring a mask with rings (McKerrow 379)</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Thomas Adams.</hi> 1617.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:25361:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>SAINT PAULS</head>
                  <figDesc>engraving of Saint Pauls Cathedral</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25361:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:25361:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25361:3"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, AND TRVLY NOBLE LORD, ROBERT LORD SPENCER, BARON of <hi>Wormelayton,</hi> Grace, mercy, and peace bee multiplied in Chriſt Ieſus.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Emembring that prouerbe, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> know thy ſelfe, I was not without much vnwillingnes drawn to preach this Sermon at the Croſſe, not being ignorant either of mine owne weakeneſſe, or of the weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe of ſo great a taske, and with much more vnwillingneſſe was I ouercome to commit it to the preſſe, for my reſolution was that as my ſubiect is of the Rainebowe, ſo my Sermon ſhould haue beene like the Rainebowe, not a permament but a vaniſhing Bowe, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing to the eies of ſome few, not remaining to be ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the iudgements of all; for <hi>comes calami calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:25361:4"/> as there are many colours of that Rainebowe in the cloudes, ſo I am ſure there will be many cenſurers of this my Rainebowe at the Croſſe; that of the Apoſtle may be applyed, <hi>vnus ſic, alter autem ſic,</hi> one iudging after this manner, another after that, one ſpeaking well, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other ill. But as commaunding Authoritie was the cauſe of the former ſo ouerruling importunitie, hath effected the latter, and now like an infant new borne, my Bowe is come naked into the world, and without a caſe. It was the ſaying of the ſpouſe in the Canti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, wee haue a little ſiſter and ſhee hath no breaſts; and I may ſay the like of this; I haue a little birde and ſhee wanteth wings; yet flie ſhee muſt into the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen ayre, and ſhift for her ſelfe: But alas what can ſhee doe, before her winges bee growne, or her ſicke feathers come to ripeneſſe? It is impoſſible that ſhee ſhould eſcape, and not be torne in peeces by the ſharpe eied vultures, (the Time-conſuming critickes) of our time, except ſome princely Eagle ſhall in pittie to ſo poore a wanderer, ſhadow her with the winges of protection; Your Honorable diſpoſition Right Noble Lord, in giuing incouragement to the Miniſters of Chriſt, hath emboldened this little birde to ſhroud her ſelfe vnder the roofe of your Honorable fauour, and my ſelfe to dedicate this firſtlinge of my ſtudies vnto your Lordſhippe, whome (with a moſt thankefull heart) I muſt euer acknowledge, my firſt incourager in my worke, ſince I haue beene a poore and vnworthy la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourer in the vineyard of Chriſt. And if at this time I may obtaine your Honorable loue in accepting this ſmall token of my thankefulneſſe, for thoſe many and
<pb facs="tcp:25361:4"/> vndeſerued fauours, conferred vpon me by your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and by that moſt Noble Knight (your Right worthy Sonne) Sir <hi>William Spencer,</hi> I ſhall receiue a moſt comfortable incitement to goe one forwards in my ſtudies, and bee for euer bound to praie for a bleſſed increaſe of all graces ſpirituall and temporall, both for this life and the life to come, vnto your Lordſhippe, your Honorable Sonne, with his Right Noble Ladie, all your Honourable progenie, and their poſteritie for euer: Reſting vntill Death.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours moſt readie in all reſpectiue ſeruice to my power. IMMANVEL BOVRNE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:25361:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:25361:5"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached at Pauls Croſſe the tenth day of Iune. 1617.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>GENESIS 9.13.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>I haue ſet my Bow in the cloud, and it ſhall bee for a ſigne of the couenant betweene me and the earth.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the rule of the Preacher,<note place="margin">Preface.</note> 
               <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> 3.1. To euery thing there is ſet time, yea, an appointed time to euery purpoſe vnder heauen. And therefore the ſame diuine and heauenly Penne-man, (wiſe and vnderſtanding <hi>Salomon</hi>) fitly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pareth a word fitly ſpoken, to apples of gold, in pictures of ſiluer, <hi>Prou.</hi> 25.11. according to which, that I might not at this time haue bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken this golden thread of beautifull order; I ſhould fitly haue ſpoken, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in the time of Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecoſt, concerning Pentecoſt. Yet becauſe I doubt not, but you haue oftentimes heard this learnedly and religiouſly handled already; I haue thought it not much out of order, (I am ſure not vnprofitable) to let paſſe the time in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and to apply my ſelfe to the time in generall, (and yet the time preſent alſo) and to ſpeake fitly of this, and of thoſe things that pertaine to the ſame, I haue choſen this portion of Scripture which I haue now read vnto you; <hi>I haue ſet my bow in the cloud, and it ſhall be for a ſigne of the Couenant, betweene me and the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Almightie God, who is wiſe in counſell,<note place="margin">Occaſion.</note> wonderfull in iudgement, and adminble in the execution of his vnſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able will, hauing manifeſted his great &amp; terrible iudgments vnto the olde world, in deſtroying them with a fearefull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge of waters, for their abominable impietie, and wilfull impenitencie, and declared his gracious fauours vnto righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:25361:6"/> 
               <hi>Noah,</hi> in ſauing him and his family in the Arke, from that moſt direfull deſtruction; hee doth for the further manifeſtation, of his vnſpeakeable goodneſſe, and moſt infinite grace, make a compact, promiſe, and couenant, betweene himſelfe, <hi>Noah,</hi> and euery liuing creature, vpon the face of the earth, and withall giueth them a ſigne, and ſeale, of the couenant, the admirable and beautifull Rainebow, for the more full and perfect confirmation of their faith; Both which ſigne, and ſignificate, the Raine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow, and the Couenant; <hi>Moſes</hi> that great Prophet of God that valiant Captaine of the hoſte of Iſrael, that meeke man aboue all the men in the earth, doth briefly expreſſe in the words of my text, <hi>I haue ſet my Bow in the cloud, and it ſall be for a ſigne of the Couenant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diuiſion.</note> 
               <hi>betweene me and the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which not to dazell the eyes of your vnderſtandings, with any quainte or curious diuiſions, (for my better dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and your better inſtruction) I doe briefly and plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, obſerue theſe particulars.</p>
            <p>Firſt the Author, of this externall ſigne the Rainebow, and of the internall ſignificate the Couenant, the omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent,<note place="margin">The firſt part. Iſaiah. 42.8. <hi>Ego ſum Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uah illud est nomen meum.</hi> Geneſ. 3.2. <hi>Spiritus</hi> ELO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HIM. <hi>a.</hi> vſ. 1. ELOHIM <hi>Bara, fortes cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auit.</hi> Gen. 7.1 Ezod. 3.14. EHEIE ASCHER EHEIE. I am that I am. ANI EL-SCHADDAI. <hi>ego ſum Deus fortis &amp;c.</hi> Iſaiah 45.12. Iſaiah 43.16.</note> and eternall God; in the firſt words, <hi>I haue ſet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the ſigne it ſelfe <hi>the Bowe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the ſituation of it, <hi>in the Cloud.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, the vſe of it, <hi>it ſhall be a for a ſigne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly and laſtly, the intimation of the internall ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, in the laſt words: <hi>of the couenant, betweene mee and the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of theſe in their order, by the aſſiſtance of Gods grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Spirit, your chriſtian patience, and permiſſion of the time.</p>
            <p>And firſt of the firſt the Author; <hi>I haue ſet:</hi> that is, I who am <hi>IEHOVAH ELOHIM,</hi> the ſtronge one, the mighty Lord of heauen, and earth, who am <hi>EHEIE;</hi> I am, alwaies the ſame, immutable, from all eternity, to all eternity: I who am <hi>EL-SCHADDAI,</hi> the ſtrong, powerfull, omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and all-ſufficient God: I who haue created the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens and the earth, and eſtabliſhed them by the word of my power, who haue made a way in the ſea, and a path in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:25361:6"/> the mighty waters,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam. 1.17.</hi> Pſallam nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni tuo Excelſe.</note> who haue ſpread out the firmament like a curtaine, and giuen the Sea her bounds, and Starres and Planets their ſeuerall influences, who am <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the Father of lights, with whom is no variableneſſe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 9.2.</note> neither ſhadow of turning; who am <hi>HELION</hi> the higheſt ouer all the earth the onely Lord and gratious deliuerer, beſides whom there is no Sauiour, in a word, I who haue deſtroyed the old world, with aboundance of waters, and haue ſaued thee my ſeruant <hi>Noah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 7.23.</note> and thy family in the multitude of my mercies, <hi>I euen I haue ſet my Bowe in the cloud, and appointed it for a ſigne of the Couenant betweene me and the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here then it is euident that,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Doctrin. God the fountaine of all grace.</note> 
               <hi>Non â nobis ſed â Deo est principium ſoederis &amp; omnis gratiae;</hi> Not of our ſelues, but of God, is the beginning of the couenant, of the ſigne of the couenant, and of all grace, fauour, and mercy: for <hi>fons gratiae, in Deo est,</hi> hee it is that is the fountaine of all grace, and the well ſpring of mercy: from the happy ſmile, of whoſe fauourable countenance, all true ioy,<note place="margin">Rom. 9.16. Eph. 2.4, 5, 6. 1. Pet. 1.3.</note> and happineſſe doth proceed, whether we reſpect the grace of Election, or the grace of effectuall vocation, the grace of iuſtification, or the grace of Sanctification, whether we reſpect temporall deliuerance,<note place="margin">Gen. 7.13, 16.</note> as of <hi>Noah</hi> from the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the old world, of <hi>Lot</hi> from the deſolation of Sodome,<note place="margin">Gen. 19.16. Exod. 15.30. Numb. 16. 32, 33, 34. Eph. 2.8.</note> and of the children of Iſrael from the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and deuouring of <hi>Corah;</hi> or the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall deliuerance of Gods elect, from the paines and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of hell fire, all proceedeth and floweth, from this well-ſpring of liuing water, from this euerlaſting fountaine, of the free grace, mercy, bounty, and goodneſſe of God; all theſe are <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the free gifts of grace,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.8. 1. Iohn 4.10.19.</note> and loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of a fauourable God; and therefore St. <hi>Iohn</hi> tells vs in this is loue, not that we loued God, but that hee loued vs, and ſent his Son to be the propitiation for our ſins, and we loue him becauſe he loued vs firſt,<note place="margin">S. Auguſt. Tom. <hi>7.</hi> lib. de bono perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantiae. cap. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> of this loue <hi>S. Auguſt.</hi> ſpeaketh excellently, <hi>Deum non diligeremus, niſi prius dilexiſſet nos, &amp; feciſſet dilectores ſuos,</hi> we ſhould not haue loued God, ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cept he had loued vs firſt, &amp; made vs to be louers of him and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:25361:7"/> he giueth the reaſon, <hi>quoniam charitas ex ipſo eſt,</hi> becauſe the fluent ſtreames of loue and charitie doe flow from him, and not from vs.<note place="margin">S. Bernard. lib. de amore c. <hi>4.</hi> Que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> admodum Nilus fluuius, Egyptum inun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam vbertate compl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, ita di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinae miſeric<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia flam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bem velu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tus C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſtibus. l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nis impleuit. Barradius Tom <hi>1.</hi> lib. <hi>8. cap. 18</hi> Plutins. lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>9. No merit in man.</hi>
               </note> And S. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſweetly, <hi>Cùm nos amas, non niſi propter te nos am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</hi> When thou loueſt vs, O God, thou loueſt vs not, but for thy ſelfe, the abounding Sea of diuine loue it is in thee, and not in vs, from whence the riuers of heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly graces doe flowe foorth moſt plentifully, and water all creatures vpon the face of the earth; but his elect and choſen Angels, and men, after a ſpeciall manner, making them fruitfull with his bleſſings, like the land of Egypt with the ouerflowing of <hi>Nilus,</hi> or the pleaſant Paradiſes of the earth, with the firſt, and latter raine of his fauours.</p>
            <p n="1">1. From this therefore it muſt neceſſarily follow, that whatſoeuer grace is granted vnto vs, (and much leſſe that eſpeciall grace of eternall happineſſe) it is not giuen vs (as the papiſts affirme and teach) for any merit, or deſert of ours, but for the free grace, and mercy, and bounty of God, in Chriſt, For if as our Sauiour commandeth, <hi>Luk</hi> 17.10.<note place="margin">Luk. 17.10.</note> when we haue done all that we can,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.8.9.</note> we muſt ſay we are vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſeruants, how then can we attribute any thing to our owne merits? if as the Apoſtle witneſſeth. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.9. we are ſaued by grace not of workes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>S. Auguſt. lib. Hom. Hom. 14. et in Pſal. 144.</hi> Merita tua nuſquam iactes quia et ipſa merita tua dei dona ſunt. <hi>Pſal. 103.4.</hi> S Auſt. de pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dect. Sanct. Humana meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta hic conticeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant que. Periere per Adam &amp; reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net Dei gratia per Ieſum Chriſtum. S Auguſt. Epiſt <hi>105.</hi>
               </note> leaſt any man ſhould boaſt, how then can we rightly boaſt of our merits? Laſtly, if that good Centurion, whoſe fayth was ſo much commended, that there was not the like to be found in all Iſrael, <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.10.<note place="margin">Mat. 8.10.</note> anſwered our Sauiour ſo humbly, with a <hi>Domine non ſum dignus;</hi> Lord I am not worthy, that thou ſhouldeſt come vnder my roofe, with what pride thinke you, are thoſe poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed, who dare ſo audaciouſly anſwer God, with a <hi>Domine dignus ſum,</hi> Lord I am worthy that thou ſhouldeſt giue vnto me eternal life. S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> he was of this good Centurions mind, and therefore he often in his workes, repeateth this one golden ſentence, <hi>Deus coronat dona ſua, non merita noſtra,</hi> God crowneth his owne giftes, and not our deſeruings, like vnto that of the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> he crowneth vs with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, and louing kindneſſe; and the ſame Father ſpeaking concerning the predeſtination of the Saints, let humane me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits (ſaith he) here be ſilent, which haue periſhed by <hi>Adam,</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:25361:7"/> and let the grace of God reigne through Ieſus Chriſt.<note place="margin">Stella in Luc. c. <hi>7.</hi> Non me aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cias, ſed vnige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitum tuum prius intuere, colloca Deus meus inter me &amp; te tuum v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigenitum fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium, crucem eius, ſanguinem &amp; paſsion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m, &amp; merita ita vt cum tua iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitia per ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinem &amp; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rita tui filii pertranſeat, cum tandem ad me perueniat iam manſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ueta &amp; miſericor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia plena ſit. Anſel in m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dit Lyran. in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſ. Epiſt. ad Rom c. <hi>6. 23.</hi> Bell. l. <hi>5</hi> de Iuſt. c. <hi>7</hi> propter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certitudol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m propriae iuſtitiae &amp; periculum manis gloriae tutiſsimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> est fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duciam tota<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſola Dei miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recordia &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignitate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponere. S. Bern. Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>68.</hi> Hoc totu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis meritum ſi totam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m ſuam pinat in eo qui to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſaluum fecit.</note> And in his 105. Epiſtle, he concludeth, <hi>Haec est gratia gratis data, non meritis operantis, ſed miſeratione donantis,</hi> This is a grace &amp; fauour which is freely giuen, not for the merit of the worker, but for the mercy of the giuer, To which accordeth that ſweete and heauenly petition of <hi>Stella,</hi> vpon the 7. of <hi>Luke.</hi> God my protector, looke not vpon me, but firſt looke vpon thine only ſonne, place betweene me and thee, his Croſſe, his blood, his paſſion, his merits, that ſo thy iuſtice paſſing through his bloud, when it commeth at the laſt to me, it may bee gentle, and full of mercy. And <hi>Anſelmus,</hi> who was ſometimes Archbiſhop of Canterburie, confeſſeth often in his Meditations, that all his life was either vnprofitable, or damnable, whereupon at the laſt hee concludeth, <hi>Quid re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtat, O peccator, niſi vt in tota vita tua, deplores totam vitam tuam;</hi> O wretched ſinner, what remaineth now to bee done, but that in thy whole life thou ſhouldeſt deplore and bewaile the ſinnes of thy whole life. To bee ſhort, <hi>Lyranus</hi> an Interpreter, approoued by the Papiſts themſelues, ſaieth plainely in his expoſition vpon that ſixt Chapter to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, and the 23. verſe, That eternall ſaluation doeth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally exceed the power of humane nature, and therefore it cannot attaine vnto it, but by the bountie of diuine mercie. And laſt of all, Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelfe, that mightie <hi>Atlas</hi> of the Papall See, in his fift Booke <hi>De Iuſtificatione,</hi> and the ſeuenth Chapter, after a long time he hath trauelled and wearied himſelfe in the queſtions of Iuſtification, at the laſt he holdeth it the onely <hi>Tutiſsimum,</hi> the ſafeſt way of all, to repoſe our whole truſt and confidence, in the ſole mercy and fauour of God. To theſe I might adde many more te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies, both of Scriptures and Fathers, to confute this Romiſh aſſertion; but I leaue it to the Schooles, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with that of S. <hi>Bernard, Meritum meum miſerationes Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini, &amp;c.</hi> my merit is the mercy of the Lord, I am not poore of merit, ſo long as hee is not poore of mercy; if his mercy be great, then am I great in merit; for this is the whole merit of man, if he put his whole confidence in the Lord.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Wherefore Beloued, we muſt not imitate the abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:25361:8"/> arrogancy,<note place="margin">All praiſe and glory to God. <hi>Allexander</hi> 3. <hi>papa, Frederico Emperat. Acts &amp; monum. volum.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 263.</note> of that proude prelate of Rome, who when he ſet his foote vpon the Emperours necke, defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, or rather cloaked his pride, with a <hi>mihi &amp; petro,</hi> to mee and to <hi>Peter,</hi> muſt bee yeelded ſubiection, when by his action it was euident, that hee rather reſpected his owne pompouſe pride, then any honour that hee would attribute vnto <hi>Peter,</hi> and therefore hee would not ſing, with that religious Kinge <hi>Dauid, Non no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis Domine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal. 115.1.</hi> Feling. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. in Can. de iure iurando. Ego. N. Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus papatum Sanct. Romanae Eccleſiae &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulas Sanctoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> patru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> adiutor ero ad defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendum &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. mutat. per P. Greg. <hi>13.</hi> in balla ad mauritiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> epiſc. Imelacenſem.</note> 
               <hi>non nobis.</hi> Not vnto vs O Lord, not vnto vs, but vnto thy name giue the praiſe, but changeth his note, and ſings after another faſhion (like many of his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents, and too too many in the world) <hi>mihi &amp; tibi da glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am domine,</hi> to mee O Lord and to thee giue the praiſe, firſt to himſelfe, and after to God, firſt reſpecting his owne profit, and pleaſure, and after the ſeruice, and glory of God.</p>
            <p>Changing his note I ſay, as his ſucceſſours haue ſince changed, that ancient forme of the oath in the Canon law, giuen to the Biſhops at their conſecration, to defend <hi>Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las ſanctorum patrum,</hi> the rules of the holy Fathers, and haue put in ſtead thereof, <hi>regalia ſancti Petri,</hi> the royalties of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> all to maintaine their owne pompoſe pride, and hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full arrogancy.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">Humility the duty of Gods children.</note>3 But whatſoeuer grace, is beſtowed vpon vs, wee muſt not be like this proude Antichriſt, or his ambitious traine, to attribute any thing to our owne worth or dignitie, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe rather with that good, and humble Saint <hi>Baſile,</hi> in his tract of humilitie.<note place="margin">S. Baſil. Tract. de humilitate.</note> This is our full and perfect reioycing in God, when wee acknowlede our ſelues, to be voide of any our owne righteouſneſſe, and to be iuſtified onely by faith in Chriſt.<note place="margin">S. Auſtin. in Pſal. <hi>94.</hi>
               </note> And with profound Saint <hi>Auguſt.</hi> vpon the 64. Pſalme, If God ſhould deale with vs according to our deſeruings he ſhould finde nothing but that he might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne,<note place="margin">S. Hieron in Iſa. cap. <hi>64.</hi>
               </note> And laſtly with S <hi>Heirom</hi> vpon <hi>Iſai.</hi> 64. chapter. If we conſider our owne merits, we muſt be driuen to deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;<note place="margin">S Auguſt. de Ciuit. dei lib. <hi>14.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> For S. <hi>Au.</hi> ſaith excellently in his 14. booke of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of God, and firſt chapter, <hi>Omnes in mortem paena debita pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipites ageret, niſi inde quoſdam in debita dei gratia liberaret,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:25361:8"/> puniſhment, would caſt all men head-long into hell, vnleſſe the vndeſerued grace of God, deliuered ſome men from it; This is the reſolution that becommeth the true ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of Chriſt, that humbling our ſelues, wee may be exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and confeſſing our owne vnworthineſſe, we may bee made worthy by the mercy of God, in Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4. To conclude this part;<note place="margin">Alſtedius in Theologia nat. part. <hi>2.</hi> Albert. magn. comment. in metor. Ariſt. Dictus eſt Deus facundiae quod hominibus elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentiam prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtare putabatur</note> God is the Authour of this Bowe, which is <hi>ſpeculum Solis,</hi> the glaſſe of the Sunne, and (as <hi>Poſsidonius</hi> calleth it) and <hi>vexillum Mercurii,</hi> the banner of Mercury, but not of that fained God, who amongſt the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans was accounted the God of eloquence, but of that great and mightie God of wiſedome, of that glorious Monarch of heauen and earth, and of this it is ſaid, that of all thoſe things, which are generated in the middle region of the aire, there is nothing more beautifull to behold, or more worthie to bee obſerued, then this Caeleſtiall Bowe. But God is the Authour of it, and therefore when wee behold the Bowe, and conſider the excellent beautie, and admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble colour thereof, wee muſt not with <hi>Cicero,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cicero de na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura Deor.</note> demaund the queſtion, why this Bowe was not accounted in the number of thoſe heathen gods; for God is Inuiſible, Eternall, and Infinite, but in the Rainebowe, there is no ſuch thing. And therefore wee muſt neither make it a god, nor fixing our mindes vpon the creature, ſtay there,<note place="margin">The creature not to be de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. Eccleſ. 43.11, 12.</note> but remember the Creatour, and praiſe continually his glorious name, wee muſt follow the counſell of the ſonne of <hi>Syrac,</hi> looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Rainebowe, and praiſe him that made it: very beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull is it in the brightneſſe thereof, it compaſſeth the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen about with a glorious circle, and the hands of the moſt High haue bended it.<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.1.</note> Wee ſhould ſing with the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> The heauens declare the glory of God, and the Firmament ſheweth his handie worke: The Sunne, the Moone, the glorious Starres, and beautifull Rainebowe, doe all ſet forth the excellent dignitie of this moſt glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and wonderfull GOD: and therefore wee may ende as the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> beginneth, <hi>Pſalme</hi> 8.<note place="margin">Pſal. 8.1.</note> the firſt verſe. O Lord our Gouernour, how excellent is thy Name in all the earth, who haſt ſet thy glory aboue the heauens, who
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:25361:9"/> haſt diuided the channels for the ouerflowings of waters, and made a way for the thunder, who canſt number the cloudes in wiſedome, and at thy pleaſure ſtay the bottles of heauen,<note place="margin">Iob 38.</note> who canſt binde the ſweet influences, of the <hi>Pleiades,</hi> and loſe the bands of Orion, who canſt bring forth Maza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roth in his ſeaſon, and guide <hi>Arcturus</hi> with his ſonnes, in a word who haſt created the light, and the darkeneſſe, the euening, and the morning, to praiſe thee, who haſt made the mightie <hi>Behemoth,</hi> the great <hi>Leuiathan,</hi> and the princely Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for thy power, who haſt ſpread out the chriſt all heauens like a glorious Canopie, and bedecked them with gliſtering ſtarres, more reſplendent then the ſparkling Diamonds; and laſt of all, who haſt ſet thy Bowe in the cloude, the beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Rainebow, for thy glory, and appointed it for a ſigne of the couenant betweene thee and the earth, which is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part of my text, the ſigne it ſelfe, the beautifull Bowe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>The ſecond part.</p>
                  <p>The ſigne it ſelfe the Bowe.</p>
               </note>
               <hi>I haue ſet my Bowe in the cloud, and appointed it for a ſigne of the Couenant betweene and the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. This Bowe without queſtion is the Rrainebowe, for firſt that is called a Bowe metaphorically, becauſe it is in forme like vnto a Bowe; ſecondly, there is no other Bowe placed of God in the cloudes, beſides the Rainebow; yet ſome there hath bin who haue made queſtion of this, affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming that by this Bowe is vnderſtood, not that heauenly Bowe, which we call the Rainebow, but ſome other thing, denotated by a metaphor, of which companie Saint <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> was one.<note place="margin">S. Ambroſe de Noe et arca. cap. <hi>27.</hi>
               </note> But the reaſons of this opinion are ſo weake, that they deſerue neither to be recited, nor refuted, and therefore with a learned diuine, I will anſwer this queſtion, with the demand of another,<note place="margin">Pererius in Geneſ.</note> 
               <hi>Quis eſt arcus qui in nubibus ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paret, &amp; cernitur ab hominibus niſi Iris?</hi> what Bow is there that doth appeare in the cloudes, or is ſeene of men beſides the Rainebow? or what elſe could be meant literally, but the Rainebow, which is myſtically a ſigne of that couenant, which God did then enter with mankinde?</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">The cauſe of the Bowe.</note>2. The efficient cauſe of this Bow, is primarily the almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God, who is <hi>primus motor, &amp; cauſa, cauſarum,</hi> the firſt moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and cauſe of all ſecond cauſes whatſoeuer; but ſeconda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:25361:9"/> the light, or beames of the Sun, in a hollow and deawie cloud, of a different proportion, right oppoſite to the Sun-beames, by the reflection of which beames, and by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe mixture of the light, and the ſhade, there is expreſſed as it were in a glaſſe, the admirable Rainebow, and the beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full colours thereof.</p>
            <p>In this Bow I doe note, firſt the forme of it,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Subdiuiſion. 1. Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
                  <p>The forme of the Bowe.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Doctrine God is moſt prone to mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Raban. Percri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us. S. Ambroſe in Gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſ. non dixit deus po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam in nubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſagittam ſed ponam ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> and ſecondly the beautifull colours that appeare in it; The forme of the Rainebow, is the figure of a ſemicircle, or a Bow, with the backe towards heauen, &amp; the two ends towardes the earth, And this is <hi>ſignum miſericordiae,</hi> a ſigne that God is more prone to mercy, then to iudgement, (as interpreters well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue,) and to ſignifie the ſame, <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> noteth, that God did not ſay, I will put my arrow in the cloud, but my Bow, and the Bow doth not wound but the arrow, ſince then it is <hi>arcus ſine ſagittis,</hi> a Bow without arrowes, it ſheweth the Bow of Gods iuſtice, which is called a Bow metaphorically, and is placed like the Rainebow, with the backe towards heauen, and the two ends towards the earth; To teach vs that God delights more in mercy then in iudgement, and therefore hath made his Bow to want arrowes,<note place="margin">2. God delights moſt in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</note> and he neuer turneth this Bow, to ſhoote the arrowes of his iudgements againſt vs, but when we firſt ſhoote vp the darts of our ſinnes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt heauen, and againſt him. But then as God turned the aſhes, which <hi>Moſes</hi> caſt vp towards heauen,<note place="margin">Exod. 9.10.</note> into a fearefull plague of boyles, and blaines, to the terrour of the Egipti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, ſo doth he turne the darts of our ſinnes, into the darts of his iudgements, and then he turneth his Bow and ſhooteth downe his arrowes, to the deſtruction of the wicked and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent. If a man will not turne, he will whet his ſword, hee hath bent his Bowe and made it readie,<note place="margin">Pſal. 7.11.</note> he hath prepared for him the inſtruments of death, he ordaineth his arrows a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the perſecutors; If men adde drunkenneſſe to thirſt and prouoke the Lords anger againſt them. If they mooue him to what his glittering ſword, and his hand take h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld on iudgement, hee will render vengeance to his enemies, and plague them that hate him:<note place="margin">Deut. 32.41, 42.</note> he will make his arrowes drunke with blood, and his ſword ſhall deuoure the fleſh of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:25361:10"/> his aduerſaries; Thus did God with our firſt parents, in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe, he helde the bowe of his iuſtice, with the backe tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards heauen, and the two endes ſignes of his mercy tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards the earth, and there was no token of his iuſtice towards them, vntill <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue,</hi> by breaking the couenant in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of the forbidden tree had darted the arrowes of their ſinnes, pride, diſobedience, and contempt of the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, againſt God their Creator, and then the Lord tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth his bowe and proceedeth in iuſtice againſt them, puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth the earth for mans ſake,<note place="margin">Gen. 3 24.</note> puniſheth man with labour and paine to get his liuing, puniſheth the woman with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row in bringing forth children, and laſtly th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſteth <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue,</hi> out of paradiſe. And for euer had they and their poſterity, beene thruſt out of the Paradiſe of heauen, had not God of his vnſpeakeable mercy, giuen them a Sauiour, the ſeede of the woman to breake the head of the Serpent.<note place="margin">Gen. 3.15. Gen. 4.11, 12 Gen. 7.21, 22 Gen. 11.8. Gen. 19.24. Ezec. 4.15, 17, 19. A motiue to repentance.</note> Thus did God with <hi>Cain,</hi> with the old world, with the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders or Babell, the wicked Sodomites, and diuerſe others, and thus will hee doe with all impenitent ſinners what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And therefore if men will not bee drawne with the bands of loue, and cordes of amitie, yet let the conſideration of Gods terrible iudgements, the turning of the Bowe of his iuſtice,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioel. 2.12.</hi> H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>huna &amp; S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hina: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rſio &amp; c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. Grace, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> &amp; ſhooting down the arrowes of his vengeance vpon wicked and impenitent ſinners, be an inuincible argument to mooue and inforce them, to a true and vnfeigned repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, to auert from their ſinnes, and conuert vnto God, and that not in part only but totally, as the Sunne is <hi>totalitèr lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minoſus,</hi> wholly inlightened.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Halfe repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is no true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sicut enim in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſitio tereae eſt cauſa E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſis ſolis ita interpoſitio pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cati eſt cauſa ecclipſis bonae conuerſionis.</p>
               </note>4. But alas, how many in the world, are rather like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Moone, ſeldome or neuer without ſome ſpot of darkeneſſe, with in the center of their hearts euermore lodging one mountaine of ſinne or other, within the cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of their breaſts, to eclipſe the glorious light of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere and holy conuerſion, and ſo of a ſacred life, and heauenly conuerſation; how many are there that can bee contented like <hi>Sampſon,</hi> to deſtroy ſome of the vncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed Philiſtims, ſome notorious and hatefull impieties.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:25361:10"/> But yet they will bee ſure to keepe in their boſomes their beloued Dalilah, their ſweete ſinne,<note place="margin">Iudges 16.17, 21.</note> in which their ſoule delighteth, and in which they take pleaſure aboue the reſt, and that they will not forſake, though they loſe both their eyes for it, as <hi>Sampſon</hi> did his, though they looſe both bodies and ſoules, and be conſtrained to grinde for euer, like milhorſes in the priſon of iniquitie, and to be made ſcoffes and laughing ſtockes, vnto their enemies, the vncircumciſed Philiſtims, the world, the fleſh, and the diuell, who both night and day, ſtill ſeeke their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; But the eſtate of theſe men is miſerable fearefull, and damnable, except they repent.</p>
            <p>For as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> concludeth,<note place="margin">S. Auguſt. Tractat. in. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>han.</note> in his tractate vpon <hi>Iohn.</hi> Becauſe they giue part vnto God, and part vnto the diuell, <hi>iratus deus quiaſit ibi pars diabolo, diſcedit, &amp; totum diabolus poſſidet.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 15.36 1. Sam. 18.10</note> God beeing angry becauſe there is part giuen to the diuell, hee departeth away as hee did from <hi>Saul,</hi> and the diuell poſſeſſeth the whole man; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that wee may eſcape the arrowes of Gods vengeance, let vs caſt downe the darts of our ſinnes, and burie them in the graue of repentance, that they may neuer aſcend towardes heauen, to pull downe Gods iudgements vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs.</p>
            <p>And that in this life while wee haue tyme, for all though the Bowe be <hi>ſignum pacis,</hi> a ſigne of peace, yet further it is to be noted from the forme and figure of it, That this Bowe is not a round circle, but a Hemiſphere, and ſhineth in one onely hemiſphere aboue the earth and not vnder the earth.</p>
            <p n="5">5 And ſo likewiſe <hi>pacis faederiſque ſigna,</hi> the ſigne of peace,<note place="margin">This life on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a time of mercy.</note> and of the couenant, the ſigne of grace, and mercie, they ſhine onely in one hemiſphere that is <hi>dum ſuper terram viui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> while we liue vpon the earth, in the other they ſhall not ſhine to the impenitent at the day of iudgement, theſe will not appeare vnto them, for they ſhall beholde them <hi>non iridem ſignum pacis ſed ſummae irae diuinae ſigna,</hi> not the Rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow the ſigne of peace, but the fearefull ſignes of Gods an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, to the horror and terror of their accuſing conſciences,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:25361:11"/> now they may beholde this heauenly Bow, without ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, and bended towards heauen, not threatning the earth, but then they ſhall beholde it full of arrowes, and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned not towards heauen, but towards the earth, bent in vengence againſt the wicked. O then beloued, let vs la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to bende him now with prayers, whom then teares will not mooue, and to pacifie him now with a ſanctified life: in whom otherwiſe at the day of iudgement we ſhal finde inexorable, and let vs ſo inioy this world, that we may haue ioy in the world to come.<note place="margin">No perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the things of this life.</note> For this Bow is not a perfect circle, although it be beautifull, and after the ſame manner all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane things, learning, wiſdome, honours, riches, beauty, and ſtrength, allthough they be faire and ſpecious endowments, yet are they not perfect in themſelues, and therefore wee muſt not labour for them, as if by them we thought to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine perfection; but ſtriue rather for that perfection, which is from God, who is the author and giuer of them all; wee muſt ſtriue for that glorious perfection, which the Saints ſhall receiue at the glorious reſurrection.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <note place="margin">The Saints neede not doubt of their glorious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection.</note>7. Of which glory the children of God need not to ſtand in doubt; For if the forme of this bowe be ſo glorious that amongſt all the meteors, there is none more illuſtrious, none more admirable, none more beautifull then it, then as often as wee looke into the admirable ſplendour thereof, it may confirme vs concerning our glorious reſurrection, for if God can make ſuch a glorious meteor, by vertue of the beames of the Sunne ſhining in the clouds, much more can he at the day of reſurrection, as the Sonne of righteouſnes, ſhining vpon our bodies, beget an admirable ſplendour, and excellent glory in them.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.53.</note> And if this mortall, muſt put on im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie, if God will make vs glorious then, in the time of iudgement, how ſhould wee labour to magnifie his glory now, in the time of mercy.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <note place="margin">The forme of the Bowe a figure of Chriſts king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</note>8. Againe this bowe doth neuer obtaine the compaſſe of a circle, or exceede the magnitude of a ſemicircle; And here lyeth a myſterie. The kingdome of Chriſt is as it were a ſphere, or round circle, deſcending from heauen vpon the earth, and aſcending from the earth towards heauen; This
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:25361:11"/> doth conſiſt of a double hemiſphere, the Church militant, and the Church triumphant, the firſt viſible, and the ſecond inuiſible; and to the perfection of this there is required the twofold comming of Chriſt, the firſt in humilitie to ſaue; and this hath his power and effectuall operation, til the day of iudgement; The ſecond in maieſtie, to reward thoſe that are ſaued, (and render vengeance to the reprobate) and the effect of this, ſhall continue to all eternitie,<note place="margin">In coelis com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plebitur hic circulus, putae regnum Chriſti dominans om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus in om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem aeternita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iem, Cornelius cornelii a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pide, Comment. in Geneſ. <hi>The perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſts kingdome a comfort to the godly.</hi>
               </note> ſince then till the day of iudgement, the efficacy of his firſt comming floriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vpon the earth, and not of his ſecond, hence ariſeth the figure of a ſemicircle, (like to the Rainebow) neither can this circle bee perfected, till the time of his ſecond comming, but then it ſhall receiue his full complement, when hee ſhall raigne over his whole Church, vnited in the fulneſſe of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for euermore.</p>
            <p>O moſt ioyfull comfort to euery faithfull ſubiect of this heauenly King, doeſt thou in feare, and loue, to this bleſſed God, labour to fulfill thy circle, to finiſh thy courſe in the hemiſphere of this life; then maieſt thou aſſure thy ſelfe, that the time ſhall come when this moſt glorious King, will compaſſe the about, with the ſphere of his glory, with the circle of his loue, with the double Rainebow of ioy, comfort, and happineſſe, for euermore.</p>
            <p n="10">10. To be ſhort the forme of the Rainebow is glorious,<note place="margin">The wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of man is blinde in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God.</note> yea it is ſo intricate, that wee cannot fully vnderſtand the nature of it, nor ſearch into the ſecrets of the glory thereof. And therefore here we may learne to acknowledge our own imperfection, and reaſon thus with our ſelues, If his workes be ſo glorious, that we cannot comprehend the excellency of them, it is no meruaile then, that our mindes are ſo darke, and our vnderſtandings ſo blinde, in the knowledge of God, of his nature, of his eſſence, of his glory, and of his moſt wonderfull properties.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Laſt of all S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> obſerueth, that the forme of this bowe, doth note myſtically the clemency of God,<note place="margin">Afflictions for the good of Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</note> for being a bow bent, but wanting arrows, it ſheweth that God giueth vs a ſight of afflictions, rather to affright vs from our ſinnes, then to ſmite vs to our hurt.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:25361:12"/>
            <p>How then ſhould we take heede, that wee prouoke not by our ſinnes this louing God, who is ſo full of clemency and mercy towards vs.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A threefold analoy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Bow and the mercy of God.</note>And of this miſticall ſignification of the Bowe, there is a threefold reaſon, taken from a threefold analogy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Bowe and the mercy of God: the firſt becauſe this Bowe was in the time of <hi>Noah</hi> a ſigne of peace, of reconciliation, and of the Couenant betweene God and men, and therefore may well note the mercy of God,<note place="margin">Ticonius Hom. <hi>2</hi> in Apocal. Rupertus &amp; Mercerus in Geneſ.</note> for which cauſe, of ſome interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, <hi>Iris</hi> is called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is peace, becauſe it did teſtifie that God was at peace with men.</p>
            <p>Secondly, this three coloured Bowe, with her diuerſe colours, and ſweete ſhowres, doth recreate, and refreſh the earth and ſo doth the mercy of God.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, as the ſemicircle doth appeare onely in our hemiſphere, in this life, ſo doth the mercy of God. And therefore how dangerouſe is the eſtate of thoſe whom the Papiſt ſhut vp in purgatory; (for they themſelues know not how many yeares) after this life: ſince there is no mercy then to bee granted vnto them. O vnmerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and terrible doctrine to frye mens ſoules ſo long in the flames of purgatory: before they ſhall receiue any part in the ioyes of Paradiſe.<note place="margin">The doctrine of Purgatory againſt the glory of Gods mercy, and derogatory to the paſſion of our Sauiour.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But this is impious againſt the glory of Gods mercy, and derogatory to the paſſion of our Sauiour; for it is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by the Scripture, that our bleſſed Lord and Sauiour Chriſt Ieſus by his one oblation by himſelfe once offered, hath made a full, perfect, &amp; ſufficient ſacrifice, and ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the ſinnes of the whole world, and this the godly are made partakers of in this life, by a true and a liuely faith, and therefore we neede not Purgatorie to purge vs after our death, ſince the bloud of Ieſus Chriſt cleanſeth vs from all ſinne, 1. Iohn 1.7.<note place="margin">1. Iohn 1.7.</note> And if from all ſinne, then certainly Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh purgatory muſt needs be excluded. For the Arke, and Dagon, Chriſt, and Beliall, the paſſion of our Sauiour, and Popiſh purgatorie, can in no wiſe agree together.</p>
            <p>And thus from the forme, caſt your eyes vpon the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:25361:12"/> beautifull colours,<note place="margin">2. Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours of the Bowe.</note> which are the ſecond thing I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued in the Bowe, <hi>I haue ſet my Bowe in the cloude, and it ſhall bee for a ſigne of the couenant, betweene mee and the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Bowe is called of the Greeke poets <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ab admiratione Garcaeus. Doct. de meteor. Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to in Theoeteto Iridem Thau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantis filiam propter admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationem di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctam cenſuit. Ariſt. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi> meteor. Aquinas in Ariſt. meteor.</note> or <hi>Thaumantis ſiue admirationis filia,</hi> the daughter of Thau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantes, or of Admiration, becauſe of all the meteors, it wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of admiration, in reſpect of the admirable, and beautiful colours that doe appeare in it; Theſe colours that appeare in the Rainebowe, they are principally three.</p>
            <p>The firſt <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Coerulean, or waterie colour.</p>
            <p>The ſecond <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the yellow, or fiery colour.</p>
            <p>The third <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the graſſie, or greene colour.</p>
            <p>And the reaſon why three colours only, doe principally appeare in the Bowe, is (as Philoſophers teach) becauſe there are only three places in the cloude, from which there is a diuerſe refraction of the light, and the ſhade, namely, <hi>ſupremus, medius, &amp; infimus,</hi> the higheſt, the middeſt, and the loweſt, and therefore there can be but three princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall colours.</p>
            <p>The Watery colour, doth note the firſt generall iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wherein the whole world was deſtroyed with water.</p>
            <p>The Fiery colour the ſecond, in which the whole world ſhall be deſtroyed with fire.</p>
            <p>The Greene colour which is a flouriſhing, and grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous colour, the preſent eſtate of grace, and mercy; by which God doth preſerue the world, from that future de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; And this obſeruation agreeth well, both with the nature, and order of theſe colours; the nature is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and the order is correſpondent;<note place="margin">Aquinas lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co citat.</note> For in the Raine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowe there is firſt the Watery colour; ſecondly, the Greene colour, and laſt of all the Fiery colour.</p>
            <p>To ſhew firſt, the iudgement of water paſt, next the ſtate of grace preſent, and laſt of all the iudgement of fire to come; But I will ſpeake firſt of the Iudgement, and after of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and firſt of the firſt iudgement, noted in the firſt colour of the Bowe, the colour of water.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:25361:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Admoniat Iris primò horrendi illius iudicii, quod in diluuio o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtenſum fuit;</hi> (ſaith a good Interpreter) The Rainbowe doeth put vs in minde,<note place="margin">The waterie colour noting the firſt iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> 
               <hi>Ferus in Geneſ.</hi> firſt of that horrible iudgement paſt, which was manifeſted in the flood: and of this the ſame writer doeth ſet downe this profitable vſe, <hi>Hinc veniemus ad cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem peccatorum, hinc diſcemus timere iudicium;</hi> Hence let vs come to the knowledge of our ſinnes, hence let vs learne to feare iudgement.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Subdiuiſion.</note>In this iudgement I find two things remarkeable: Firſt, their Sinne. And ſecondly, their puniſhment.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">The ſinne of the old world intolerable.</note>1. Firſt, their ſinne was intollerable; for it was vniuerſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpread ouer all kinde of people, ouer all parts of the world; It had continued almoſt a thouſand, or at leaſt ſeuen hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares, from the tranſlation of <hi>Enoch,</hi> when eſpecially it began to increaſe, (as interpreters well obſerue) they were poſſeſſed with a deadneſſe of heart,<note place="margin">Parreus in Geneſ.</note> and careleſſe ſecuritie, with contempt of Religion, with contempt of <hi>Noah</hi> the Preacher of righteouſneſſe, and with contempt and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God himſelfe: To conclude, ſo hatefull was their ſinne in the ſight of God, that it repented the Lord, that hee had made man on the earth, and it grieued him at his heart. 2.<note place="margin">No repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce properly in God. <hi>Theodoret in Geneſ. cap.</hi> 7. Numb. 23.19 Malac. 3.6. <hi>Lyra &amp; Gloſſa in Geneſ.</hi>
               </note> Not that there is any repentance properly to bee found in God: For as <hi>Theodoret</hi> demaundeth the queſtion, <hi>Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo poenitentia cadat in eum, qui ſuâ praeſcientiâ regit vniuerſa:</hi> How ſhould repentance be found in him, who by his eternal preſcience, and foreknowledge, doeth gouerne all things. But <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, figuratiuely, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſpeaking af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the manner of men; <hi>Non ſecundum rem, ſed ſecundum modum,</hi> not according to the thing, but according to the manner of the thing, as <hi>Lyra,</hi> and the ordinary Gloſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret, according to that golden rule of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Theſe things are ſpoken humanely, but they are to bee vnderſtood diuinely, that is, as they are agreeable, and anſwerable to the nature of God.<note place="margin">Greg. magnus in Iob, lib. <hi>20.</hi> cap. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> And therefore <hi>Gregory</hi> the great doeth wittily, and pithily conclude, concerning God, in his morall expoſition vpon <hi>Iob, quia ipſe immutabilis, id quod voluerit mutat, paenitere dicitur, quamuis rem mut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, conſilium non mutet:</hi> Becauſe God
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:25361:13"/> himſelfe being immutable, doeth change that which hee hath willed, he is ſaid to repent, although indeed he doeth change the thing, but doeth neuer change his counſell, and eternall Decree. And thus it repented the Lord, (that is, as <hi>Moſes</hi> doeth expreſſe the hatred of ſinne in the ſight of God,<note place="margin">The puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the old world grieuous.</note> according to the capacitie of men) and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their ſinne was intollerable. And their puniſhment (which is the next circumſtance) was likewiſe grieuous: Firſt, in reſpect of the Authour of it, a mightie, powerfull, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and terrible God, who is a conſuming fire to the wicked,<note place="margin">Hebr. 12.29.</note> and a lake of brimſtone to the workers of iniquitie. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> in reſpect of the time, which was the Spring,<note place="margin">S. Ambroſ. in Geneſ. Secundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſem verni tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris fuiſſe non ambigitur.</note> as the moſt and beſt Expoſitours doe iudge, to the greater griefe of the wicked, becauſe they were taken away in their pleaſure, and the world was drowned when the earth was filled in great abundance. Thirdly, in reſpect of the manner of it: for then were the fountaines of the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> great deepe broken vp, and the mightie cataracts, and flood-gates of heauen opened; the ſtreames of water guſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed foorth, with a terrible noyſe, and a dolefull roaring from the heauen and from the earth, from aboue and from belowe, on the right hand, and one the left: ſo that there was no way to eſcape from the reuenging hand of an angry God.</p>
            <p>To conclude, it was grieuous and terrible, in reſpect of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> the effect of it: for (excepting <hi>Noah,</hi> and the reſt in the Arke) all fleſh died, that were on the earth, there was none that was ſaued, no not one: the husband and the wife, the father and the ſonne, the mother and the daughter, the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and the ſeruant, the olde and the young, they were all drowned together.</p>
            <p>O then beloued, what heart can there be in the world ſo hard and ſlonie, what eyes ſo flintie, that cannot melt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to briniſh teares, and breake in pieces with griefe and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, at the conſideration of ſo lamentable a ſpectacle: Good GOD,<note place="margin">Mans dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable.</note> that euer man ſhould ſo farre degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from his firſt integritie, and fall into ſuch vile impieties, which could prouoke ſo gracious a God, to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:25361:14"/> plague him with ſo terrible a deſtruction. But man is fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, man is degenerated from his firſt integritie, who can but lament with a dolefull lamentation, God is angrie, hee hath ſmitten, hee hath plagued, he hath drowned the olde world, with a dolefull iudgement, who can but quake with fearefull tremblings? What man is there vnder the cope of heauen, that cannot by this be mooued to remooue his hatefull ſinnes, the cauſes of Gods direful puniſhments, ſince for them God is mooued to deſtroy, not onely man, but the bruite creatures together with man, the ſoules of the ayre, the beaſts of the field, and the creeping things of the earth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Obiection.</note>
               <hi>Sed quid hi fecerunt?</hi> But what haue theſe done, may ſome man obiect? will the Lord deſtroy the righteous with the wicked? ſhal not the Iudge of all the world do right? is there the ſame condition of him that ſinneth, &amp; him that ſinneth not? what had the beaſts of the field offended? wherin had the creeping things of the earth ſinned, or what iniquitie had the foules of the heauen committed, that they alſo muſt be deſtroyed with man?<note place="margin" type="runSum">Solution. The creatures deſtroied in the flood for a threefold reaſon.</note> To which I anſwere, that as all theſe were created in the beginning for man, and for the good of man, ſo they were all againe deſtroyed with man, for the ſinne &amp; puniſhment of man, by the iuſt iudgment of God: Firſt, becauſe man was become a rebellious traitour <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> againſt God his Creator, &amp; therfore as a King condemning a perfidious rebell, doeth not only command him to be put to a ſhamefull death; but his lands, goods, and chattels to be confiſcate: ſo likewiſe God doeth not onely deſtroy man, but the creatures together with man, which were created <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> for his vſe. Secondly, becauſe that beaſtly men had abuſed the creatures by their filthy pleaſure, and riotous exceſſe; and therefore it ſtood with Gods iuſtice, to puniſh the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> with the principall. Laſtly, to ſhew the hatefull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinne in the ſight of God, hee beeing Lord of all, doeth not onely deſtroy man, but the bruite creatures to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with man, as before he did curſe the earth for mans ſake, <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 3.17.</p>
            <p>If then thou wilt not bee mooued for thine owne ſake
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:25361:14"/> to refraine from thy ſinnes, and remooue thy impieties;<note place="margin">The deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the beaſts ſhould mooue vs to remooue our ſinnes.</note> yet take pitie vpon the bruite beaſts, vpon the creeping things, vpon the foules of the ayre, leſt by thy ſinnes thou pull downe Gods terrible iudgements, and they alſo periſh with thee. If thou wilt not bee mooued for any of theſe, yet take pitie vpon thy ſeruants, vpon thy little children, vpon thy wife that lieth in thy boſome, leſt thou prouoke Gods anger againſt thee, and they alſo periſh with thee.</p>
            <p>But, <hi>O corda ſaxis duriora!</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mens hearts more hard then adama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts.</note> O hearts more hard then adamants! how many are there in the world, that cannot bee mooued for any of theſe, nor for all theſe, nor for greater motiues then theſe, to remooue their ſinnes, and forſake their impieties? For although they haue often heard of that ineſtimable loue of God towards mankinde, in that hee ſpared not his owne Sonne, but gaue him to the death for vs miſerable ſinners; yet are they nothing hereby mooued to repentance, although they haue often heard of that vnſpeakeable loue of Chriſt, in that hee ſpared not his owne life, but offered vp his body vpon the Altar of the Croſſe, a ſweet ſmelling incenſe of reconciliation to God his Father for our redemption: yet are they nothing here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by mooued to repentance. In a word, they can neither be mooued by threatnings, nor by promiſes, by iudgements, nor by mercies, by the terrible deſtruction of the old world, nor by the bitter paſſion of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And this is common in this age of the world,<note place="margin">The commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſpoſition of this age of the world.</note> as it was common in the dayes of <hi>Noah:</hi> yea, if wee make a paralel, and compariſon betweene the ſinnes of this age, and the impieties of the old world, wee ſhall finde that the iniquitie of theſe daies, is as great, if not greater, then euer were the ſinnes of the olde world. And therefore I may ſay to the men of this age, as our Sauiour ſaid to thoſe Iewes (who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded the queſtion concerning the Galilaeans, whoſe blood <hi>Pilate</hi> had mingled with their ſacrifices: and of thoſe eighteen, vpon whom the tower of Siloe fel,<note place="margin">Luke 13.5.</note> and ſlew them) except ye repent, ye ſhall all likewiſe periſh: For if God ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not the Angels which ſinned,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.4, 5, 6</note> but caſt them downe to hell, and kept them in chaines of darkeneſſe, reſerued to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:25361:15"/> iudgement. If hee ſpared not the olde world, but ſaued <hi>Noah</hi> the eight perſon, a Preacher of righteouſneſſe, bringing in the flood vpon the world of the vngodly: If hee ſpared not the Cities of Sodome and Gomorrah, but turned them into aſhes, and condemned them with an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow, making them an example to thoſe which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhould liue vngodly. Then certainely, neither will hee ſpare this age of the world, except in time they turne from their ſinnes: and therefore I may iuſtly ſay with our Sauiour, Except they repent, they ſhall all likewiſe periſh; the reaſon is, becauſe the ſinnes of this age, doe paralel the impieties of the old world, which wil euidently appeare, if we make our compariſon.</p>
            <p>For firſt, the ſinne of the olde world was exceeding great, beeing vniuerſally ſpread ouer all parts of the world, ouer all ſorts of men. And is it not ſo in this age of the world? Who can ſay, <hi>Munda est vita mea;</hi> my life is cleane, and I am free from iniquitie: there is none I am ſure: for all fleſh haue corrupted their wayes; yea, the greater ſort of men continue in their ſinnes, and goe on forward in their wickedneſſe, metamorphizing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues into bruitiſh creatures, by their vnreaſonable impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eties, and beaſtly iniquities.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>1. Paralel.</hi> Plat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ibus Crudel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>as in ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>cit, v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>am eg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>S.</hi> Aug. in Ser. Auarus veluti inf rn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s omnia deuorant villet nullum homine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſe, vt omnia ſolus poſsideret. S. Aug. de ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis Dom. Inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt ſilia ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbiae. ſed iſta mater ſuperbia n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcit eſſe ſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis vbi fuerit, continuo parit, ſuffoca matre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; non erit ſilia <hi>2. Sam. 20.9.</hi> S. Greg. lib. <hi>8.</hi> moral. Quid eſt vita hypocrita niſi quaedam viſio phantaſmatis qua hic oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit in imagine quod non habet in veritate.</note>Some are like Lions, in their abominable crueltie, ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vp the earth with opp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſion, and ſacriledge, without any mercie, pittie, or compaſſion. Some are like Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gars, in their raging violence, deuouring all that commeth to their handes, without any reſpect either of God, or of men. Some are like vnto Foxes, in their craft and ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, delighting in nothing but guile, and deceite. Some are like Serpents in their malice and hatred, as if they were compoſed of enuie and gall. Some are like Syrens in their wicked hypocriſie, they will ſpeake faire to a mans face, till they haue him in their compaſſe, and then they will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure him in their blood-ſucking tyranny. Some are like Apes in their apiſh imitation, <hi>Proteus</hi> like, changing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues into all ſhapes, that they may bee fitted for all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies. Laſtly, ſome are like Aſſes in their ſottiſh igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:25361:15"/> and ſenſeleſſe ſecuritie, beeing nothing affrighted, with the feare of Gods iudgements, nor mooued with his mercy, But as if their conſciences were ſeared; in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite of reprehenſion, will continue impenitent, and conclude, ſome are like dogges,<note place="margin">2. Peter 2.32.</note> that returne to their vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of ſinne, and like the Sow that was waſhed, to the filthy puddle, of their hatefull impieties. And therefore I may ſay with our Sauiour, except they repent, they ſhall all like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe periſh.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">2. Paralel.</note> the ſinne of the old world was exceeding great, for it was come to the height of impietie, And is it not ſo in this age? was their euer more ſhameleſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in ſinning, then in theſe daies? was their euer leſſe conſcience of iniquitie, then in theſe times?</p>
            <p>It would bee too late for mee, to tell you, what a floud of vngodlineſſe, hath now ouerſpread the face of the earth, the time would not ſuffer mee, to relate vnto you, what drunkenneſſe, and adulterie, what ſacriledge, and ſimonie, what oppreſſion, and crueltie, what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortion, and bribery, what vſury, and periurie, and what abhominable impietie, is euery where to be found in the actions of men, yea ſuch iniquities as were neuer to bee found in the old world. And therefore except they repent, they ſhall all likewiſe periſh.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the ſinne of the old world, was exceeding great,<note place="margin">3. Paralel.</note> for not only the wicked, but the ſonnes of God, fell to folly and iniquitie, And is it not ſo in this age of the world? Doe not thoſe that are the children of God, oftentimes yeeld to the temptation of Satan, and intiſements of the world to the diſhonour of God, and griefe of his ſpirit?<note place="margin">Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren not without im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections.</note> Doe not too too many of thoſe, that make a ſhew, and profeſſion of religion, cauſe the name of God to bee euill ſpoken of, and giue occaſion to the world; to brand their names, with the note of hypocriſie, becauſe their conuerſation is not anſwerable to their profeſſion? it is euident they doe and therefore except they repent, they ſhall all likewiſe periſh.<note place="margin">4. Paralel.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, the ſinne of the old world was exceeding
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:25361:16"/> great, for it was not ſhort but had continued a long time, all moſt a thouſand, or at the leaſt ſeuen hundred yeares, ſo that they were growne to an habite in iniquitie, and is it not ſo in this age? are not men growne to a habite in ſinne? hath not the wickedneſſe of the world continued, not ſeuen hundred or a thouſand, but aboue three thouſand yeares? and yet doth it not remaine, as ſtrong as euer it did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore? it is euident it doth, and therefore except they repent, they ſhall all likewiſe periſh.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">5. Paralel.</note>Fiftly, the ſinne of the old world was exceeding great, for they were poſſeſſed with deadneſſe of heart, and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſecurity, ſo that neither by threatning, nor particular iudgements, they could be drawen to repentance; and is it not ſo in this age of the world? was there euer more deadneſſe of heart, &amp; careleſſe ſecuritie, then in theſe daies? Hath not God ſent downe many terrible and feareful iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments vpon the world?<note place="margin">The hardnes of mens hearts cannot be remooued by Gods iudgements.</note> yea vpon this land, within this few yeares? and yet notwithſtanding, the hearts of men re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine hardened, and they continue ſtill in their ſinnes? It is true indeede, God hath promiſed, that he wil neuer againe deſtroy the whole world with water; yet he did neuer promiſe, that he would not deſtroy, this or that particular king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, country, citie, for then we might haue ſome ſhewes, to preſume of ſafety. But how many warnings haue we had, either to put vs in minde, of that generall iudgement paſt, in which the whole world (except <hi>Noah</hi> and his family) were drowned, to mooue vs to repentance, or to put vs in minde, of ſome fearefull iudgement to come, becauſe of our impenitency,<note place="margin">In Deuon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire by breach of the ſea and other places.</note> what inundations, what flowings, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowings of waters: within this few yeares, in diuers parts of this kingdome, to the deſtroying of townes, and fields of men, women, and children; of beaſts, cattle, and creeping things; and yet notwithſtanding, the hearts of men remaine hardened, and they continue ſtill in their ſinnes. Againe God hath threatned (we know it all) to bring one generall iudgement more, and to deſtroy the world with fire, (as I ſhall ſhew you fully in the next circumſtance.) And what alarums, and dreadfull warning peeces haue we had, of this
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:25361:16"/> terrible iudgement? what lamentations,<note place="margin">Harbingers of that terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble fire.</note> and dolefull cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, haue we daily heard in our ſtreetes? of fire, fire, and deſolation by fire, al moſt from euery part of the kingdome; to put vs in mind of that dreadful fire, which ſhal deſtroy the whole world, we know not how ſoone; beſides many other particular iudgements, the ſword, the famine, &amp; the fearefull peſtilence, ſo oftentimes threatned againſt vs, and yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the hearts of men remaine hardened; and they continue ſtill in their ſins. And therefore I may iuſtly ſay with our Sauiour, except they repent they ſhall all like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe periſh.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, the ſinne of the old world was exceeding great,<note place="margin">6. Paralel.</note> for they were poſſeſſed with contempt of religion, with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of <hi>Noah</hi> the preacher of righteouſneſſe, and with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and deſpiſing of God himſelfe. And is it not ſo in this age of the world? was there euermore contempt of religion, then in theſe daies? was there euer more contempt of the preachers of righteouſneſſe, then in theſe times? Nay, was there euer more contempt, deſpiſing of God himſelfe, then is extant in the world at this very houre? Certainly no, for mens wicked liues will plainly teſtifie, that the contempt of theſe daies, is as great, if not greater, then euer was the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, of the old world; In the old world they had but one <hi>Noah,</hi> whom eſpecially they contemned, and for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of whom, they are eſpecially branded, but in this age of the world, how many hundreds of <hi>Noahs</hi> are there, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of righteouſneſſe, whoſe exhortations, and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, are daily contemned, to the diſhonour of God, and griefe of good men; How many churliſh <hi>Nabals,</hi> that are readie rather to rob them of their neceſſarie maintenance, then to reward them for their paines and care in watching,<note place="margin">Ioel 2.12. Matth. 5.4. <hi>S. Bern. in Cant.</hi> The teares of the penitent are the wine of Angels, &amp;c.</note> and defending, not their ſheepe, but their ſoules, from thoſe ſpirituall wilde beaſts, that ſeeke their deſtruction.</p>
            <p>But O beloued, let vs all turne vnto the Lord with faſting, with weeping, and with mourning, that the Lord may turne in mercy vnto vs, and keepe away his fierce wrath from vs, euen for the merits of Chriſt our Sauiour, and let euery faithfull Chriſtian ſay, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:25361:17"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>S. Auguſt. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt. Natiuit.</hi> the teares of the penitent fall in the ſight of the Lord. The fiery co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour noting the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of fire.</note>That ſo making a true vſe of this firſt generall iudgement, noted in the firſt colour of the Rainebowe, the colour of water, wee may be ſure to eſcape with ioy, and reioycing, from that ſecond generall, but more terrible iudgement, noted in the ſecond colour, the colour of fire, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth in the next place, to be ſpoken of, <hi>I haue ſet my Bowe in the Cloud, and it ſhall be as a couenant, betweene mee and the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this I will paſſe through three paſſages, and handle three particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Subdiuiſion. Mat. 25.34.</note>Firſt, the time, Secondly, the manner, and Thirdly, the end, and vſe (to vs) of this fiery iudgement, or iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by fire. The time is the firſt in order, and for the time of the ſentence; our Sauiour ſets it downe <hi>Math.</hi> 25.34. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> then ſhall the King ſay to them on his right hand, come ye bleſſed of my father, receiue the kingdome prepared for you, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, from the foundation of the world: this muſt be after the Sonne of man is come with his glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Angels, and hath made a ſeparation betweene the ſheepe, and the goatet, the wheate, and the tares, the idle loyterers, and the painefull labourers in the vineyard of Chriſt. But for the time when this ſeperation ſhall bee, or when this Sonne of man ſhall come, <hi>nihil certi ex ſacris literis habetur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nazianzen: orat. 36.</hi> Horam cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam habet vt Deus ignorat vt homo. Ambroſe in Luk. <hi>17.</hi> Chriſtus hora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nouit, ſed nouit ſibi mihi neſcit. S. Auguſt. lib. <hi>1</hi> de Trinit. c. <hi>12.</hi> Greg. epiſt. <hi>42.</hi> Hilar. de Trin. Greg lib <hi>8.</hi> epiſt. <hi>42.</hi> ad eulog.</note> there is no certainty to be found in holy Scripture, for of that day and hower, knoweth no man, no not the Angels in heauen, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but the Father only, <hi>Math.</hi> 24.36. no not the Sonne himſelfe, <hi>Mark.</hi> 13.32. The Sonne knoweth not the day of iudgement, that is, not as he is man, although he knoweth it as he is God: or hee know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not the day of iudgement, that is, as S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> noteth he knoweth for himſelfe, although hee will not reueale it vnto vs: to whom S. <hi>Auguſtine, Gregory,</hi> and <hi>Hilary</hi> accord. And therefore S. <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> well obſerueth, in that Chriſt Ieſus ſaid, <hi>neque Angeli,</hi> neither the Angels know this day, he repreſſed his diſciples, that they ſhould not deſire to know, that which the Angels themſelues were ignorant of; but in that hee ſaith, neither the Sonne himſelfe, hee doth forbid them not onely from learning, but alſo from deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:25361:17"/> to learne ſo ſecret a myſterie.<note place="margin">Chriſtus nouit diem iudicij in natura huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatis non ex natura humae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatis.</note> And for this cauſe hee tells his diſciples plainely, <hi>Actes</hi> 1.7. <hi>Non est veſtrum noſce tempora,</hi> it is not for you to know the times and the ſeaſons, which God the Father hath put, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in his owne hand.</p>
            <p>But contrarie to this hath been the practiſe of thoſe,<note place="margin">S. Aug. li. <hi>8.</hi> de ciuit. Dei ca. <hi>53</hi> Fruſtra annos qui huic ſeculo r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>manent co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare ac deſtaire conamur cunt hoc ſcire non eſſe noſtrum ex ore veritatis audiamus. <hi>Gene. 19.26. The day of iudgement not to be ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched into.</hi> Oraculum e ſchola Eliae. Pet. Mart. loc. Com. <hi>Three opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the day of iudgement.</hi>
               </note> who daring to outface the Sunne, in beholding the bright ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his glorious beames, and ſearching into ſecrets, not to be looked into, haue dazelled their eyes, and left their erronious opinions, teſtimonies of their vile preſumption. Some like <hi>Lots</hi> wife, haue not beene afraid to looke backe towards Sodome, and to prie into Gods ſecret iudgements, contrary to the admonition of the Angell; yea, to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt himſelfe, ſetting downe, and defining a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminate time to the day of iudgment, producing an oracle (as they faine) from the ſchoole of one <hi>Elia</hi> a Iew, by which they affirme, that the world ſhould continue ſixe thouſand yeares, which they account thus; two thouſand before the Law, two thouſand vnder the Law, and two thouſand in the kingdome of Chriſt. But for this preſcription of time, wee haue no warrant from the word of God, and therefore we may iuſtly refuſe it. Others there are, who differ but little from the former, teaching, that as God was ſixe dayes in creating the world, ſo he ſhall bee ſixe dayes in gouerning of it, accounting to euery day a thouſand yeares, and alledging for their ground, that of the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> in the 90. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> verſe 4. A thouſand yeares in thy ſight,<note place="margin">Pſal. 90.4.</note> are but as yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> which is paſt. But concerning that place of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, the meaning i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, that innumerable yeares is but as a ſhort time with God: And wee may as well ſay two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, or ten thouſand yeares are but as yeſterday, as a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, ſince all is alike with God, with whom there is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Prius,</hi> nor <hi>Posterius;</hi> no difference of time, for hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth alwayes the ſame, throughout all generations, and his yeares haue no end, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 102.27. And I am God,<note place="margin">Pſal. 102.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7. Malac. 3.6.</note> I change not, and ye ſonnes of <hi>Iacob</hi> are not conſumed, <hi>Malac.</hi> 3.6. we cannot therefore approoue of this neither, becauſe it cannot be prooued out of the word of God.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:25361:18"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> A third ſort there is, who affirme, that as Chriſt was thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie three yeares with his naturall body vpon the earth, ſo he ſhall remaine thirtie three yeares with his myſticall body the Church, accounting to euery yeare fiftie yeares, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them like to the yeares of Iubely,<note place="margin">Leuit. 25.11</note> which did conſiſt of fiftie yeares, <hi>Leuit.</hi> 25 11. So that by this account, it ſhould be from the birth of Chriſt, vnto the end of the world, one thouſand ſixe hundred and fiftie yeares; and therefore not aboue thirtie foure yeares to the day of iudgement. But all theſe are <hi>figmenta hominum,</hi> the deuiſes of men, and therfore not to be beleeued.<note place="margin">S. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>guſt. ad H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſich<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n.</note> Excellent is that anſwere of S. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> vnto <hi>Heſichius,</hi> to whom enquiring curiouſly of the end of the world, <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> anſwereth, <hi>Se non audere ſpacia ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culorum, vſqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ad finem mundi, aut metiri, aut enumerare,</hi> that he durſt not either number, or meaſure the times of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges vnto the end of the world, becauſe it is written, Of that day and houre knoweth no man, no not the Angels in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, <hi>Math.</hi> 24.36.<note place="margin">Math. 24.36.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> It is ſufficient for vs to know that it is the laſt time, and therefore not long to the day of Iudgement,<note place="margin">Theſe are the laſt times. <hi>S Auguſt in Geneſ lib.</hi> 1. Sixe ages of the world.</note> and end of the world. For as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> obſerueth in his firſt booke vpon <hi>Geneſis,</hi> there are ſixe ages of the world; the firſt, from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> vnto <hi>Noah:</hi> the ſecond, from <hi>Noah</hi> vnto <hi>A raham:</hi> the third, from <hi>Abraham</hi> to <hi>Dauid:</hi> the fourth, from <hi>Dauid</hi> to the captiuitie of Babylon: the fift, from the captiuitie of Babylon vnto Chriſt: and the ſixt and laſt, from Chriſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the end of the world. And of theſe ages, fiue are whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paſſed already; and of the ſixt and laſt, there are 1616. yeares expired:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.11.</note> and therefore if S. <hi>Paul</hi> in his dayes affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vnto the Corinthians, that the ends of the world were come vpon them.<note place="margin">1. Peter 4.7.</note> and S. <hi>Peter</hi> in his time, that the ende of all things was at hand, which is aboue fifteene hundred yeares ſince,<note place="margin">1. Iohn 2.18.</note> then may wee iuſtly verifie with S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> that it is the laſt time, and with <hi>S. Iames,</hi> that the Iudge ſtandeth before the doore.<note place="margin">Iames 5.9. Signes of the day of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of two ſorts.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Seeing almoſt all the ſignes that were to come before the day of Iudgement, are already paſt and expired, or elſe now manifeſt in the world: for theſe ſignes are of two ſorts,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:25361:18"/> the firſt, <hi>Signa praecedentia,</hi> precedent ſignes: the ſecond, <hi>coniuncta,</hi> (or rather <hi>concomitantia,</hi> as the Logicians ſpeake) ſignes accompanying the day of iudgement. Of the firſt ſort, there are diuers noted in the Scripture, as the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Goſpell throughout all nations:<note place="margin">Mat. 24.14. 2. Theſ. 2.3. 2. Tim. 3.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. Math. 24.6, 7. Rom. 11.25, 26.</note> the comming of Antichriſt: the departing away from the faith: the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall corruption of the world, and vniuerſalitie of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, warres, and rumours of warre, deadneſſe of heart, with careleſſe ſecuritie: and laſt of all, the calling of the Iewes. But of time, and manner, and where, it is not yet concluded amongſt learned Diuines. Howſoeuer, the moſt of theſe ſignes are fulfilled alreadie.</p>
            <p>And for the ſecond ſort, they are ſet downe by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, <hi>Mathew</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">Math. 24.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here ſhall bee ſignes in the Sunne, in the Moone, and in the Starres, and then ſhall appeare the ſigne of the Sonne of man in heauen, and all the Tribes of the earth ſhall mourne, and they ſhall ſee the Sonne of man comming in the cloudes of heauen,<note place="margin">Reuel. 1.7.</note> with power and great glory. Fearefull and terrible ſhall theſe ſignes bee: And therefore while the Sonne of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe CHRIST IESVS, is in the ſignes of mercie,<note place="margin">Sol Chriſtus luna est <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a.</note> and the Moone in the fulneſſe of grace, before the Sunne bee turned into darkeneſſe, and the Moone into blood; while God doeth with patience expect our conuerſion,<note place="margin">Conuerſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on nec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry in the time of me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y. Hebr. 12.29. <hi>Greg in H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m.</hi> 13 <hi>in Euang.</hi>
               </note> let vs turne vnto him, leſt when he ſhall paſſe to the ſignes of iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtice, hee puniſh with the ſeueritie of his iudgements. For our God is a conſuming fire, ſaith the Apoſtle. And <hi>S. Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie, Hom.</hi> 13. vpon the Euangeliſts, <hi>Deus quos diu vt conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantur t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lerat, non conuerſos, durius damnat:</hi> thoſe whom a long time God doeth ſuffer, expecting their conuerſion, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conuerted hee condemneth them with the greater ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueritie. <hi>Dulcis &amp; rectus, dicitur Dominus,</hi> the Lord is ſaid to be gracious and righteous, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 25.7.<note place="margin">Pſal. 25.7</note> Hee is now gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, becauſe hee doeth offer the ſweetneſſe of his mercie vnto the wicked, that they might not periſh: but in the daye of iudgment, he ſhall bee found iuſt and righteous, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he wil iuſtly condemne thoſe then, who haue contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the grace and mercy that he offers them now.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:25361:19"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">S. Barnard. ſerm. <hi>2.</hi> de ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent. dom.</note>Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> in this reſpect compareth God vnto a Bee, which hath not only ſweet and pleaſant honie, but alſo a ſharpe and terrible ſting, <hi>nunc mel offert, in iudicio figet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culeum.</hi> Now hee offers honie, but at the day of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hee ſhall put forth his ſting, and wound the wicked: Chriſt at his firſt comming brought hony,<note place="margin">Chriſtus veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> mel attulit n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n acculeum. Idem eod. S. Auguſt. in Pſal. <hi>74.</hi> Non eſt quo fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gias a deo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to niſi ad pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum. <hi>That there ſhal be a time iudgement of it is certaine.</hi>
               </note> and not a ſting, <hi>Sed nolite peccare in ſpe,</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Bernard</hi>) but ſinne not in hope, whoſoeuer ye bee that delight in ſinne, for this our Bee hath a time alſo, when hee will take his ſtinge, and fixe it into the bones and marrow, of the reprobate? what ſhould we doe then beloued, but flie vnto him now, while wee haue time, leaſt one day we labour to flie from him, when we ſhall haue neither time nor place.</p>
            <p n="6">6. But certaine it is that there ſhall be a time of iudgment, as there is and hath beene a time of mercy, ſince it is fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured by ſo many ſignes, prooued by ſo many teſtimonies, and foretold by ſo many prophecies in the holy Scriptures.</p>
            <p>And therefore thoſe are iuſtly confuted, who haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to obiect, that becauſe there is a priuate iudgment of euery particular man,<note place="margin">An Obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> at the day of his death therefore there ſhal be no generall iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t at the day of reſurrection: for <hi>res ſemel iudicata, bis non iudicatur</hi> (ſay they) that which is once iudged, ſhould not be iudged againe: ſince the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe teſtifieth by his Prophet, <hi>Nahum</hi> 1.9.<note place="margin">Nahum 1.9.</note> 
               <hi>Non conſurget duplex tribulatio,</hi> affliction ſhall not ariſe the ſecond time, and therefore iudgement ſhall not twiſe be executed.</p>
            <p>I anſwer with that Angelicall Doctor <hi>Aquinas, in</hi> 4. <hi>ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiarum diſtinct.</hi> 47.<note place="margin">An anſwer. <hi>Aquinas</hi> 4. <hi>ſent. diſtinct.</hi> 47.</note> 
               <hi>iudicari primo illo animam potiorem hominis partem, tandem altero hominem totum,</hi> that in that firſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the ſoule of man, only is iudged, which is his better part, but in the ſecond the whole man ſhall bee iudged, both in body and ſoule, and receiue either that bleſſed ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of abſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or that fearefull ſentence of condemnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>And concerning that place of the Prophet, I Anſwer, that the Prophet <hi>Nahum</hi> ſpeaketh not there,<note place="margin">Nahum 1.9.</note> either of the generall or particular iudgement, to eternall life, or death but of a temporall iudgement, for declaring the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the Aſſyrians, hee ſheweth only that their
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:25361:19"/> ouerthrow ſhould bee finall, that God ſhould not neede to ſmite them againe the ſecond time, as <hi>Abiſha</hi> ſaid to <hi>Dauid,</hi> when hee found <hi>Saul</hi> aſleepe, let mee ſmite him, and I will not ſmite him againe, 1. <hi>Samuel</hi> 26. verſ. 9.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 26.9.</note> for hee would haue ſlaine him at the firſt blowe. And thus <hi>Theophilact</hi> and <hi>Theodoret</hi> expound that place, ſo that we may ſtill hold the concluſion, that as the day of iudgement is figured, prooued, and prophecied, ſo it ſhall certainely come at the day appointed.</p>
            <p>To conclude,<note place="margin">The day of iudgement draweth nigh at hand. Heb. 10.27.</note> it is likewiſe certaine that the time of this comming to iudgement is not farre off, but draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth nigh at hand to bee fulfilled, for as the Apoſtle ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, <hi>Hebrewes</hi> 10. and the 37. verſe. Yet a very little while, and hee that ſhall come, will come, and will not tarry, and if this were true in the morning of this age, it muſt needs bee much more true in the euening, which is ſo many hundred yeares after, and therefore here is an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to that common obiection, of wicked and irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Atheiſts, which abound in the world, who are not aſhamed to affirme, if not in their words, yet in their liues and conuerſations, that let the Ambaſſadours of God, ſay what they will they neede not bee ſo carefull to forſake their profitable, or pleaſurable ſinnes; for the day of Doome (as they call it) that is farre off, God know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth when that will bee, (euer or neuer) and therefore they may liue yet as they liſte, and repent hereafter when they can bee at leiſure.</p>
            <p>But to theſe raging waues of the ſea, foaming out their owne ſhame, (vnleſſe they repent in time) is reſerued the blackeneſſe of darkeneſſe for euer,<note place="margin">Iude 13.</note> as Saint <hi>Iude</hi> ſpeaketh in the 13. verſe of his Epiſtle.</p>
            <p>And know this whoſoeuer thou art that foſtereſt thy ſelfe in this opinion,<note place="margin">Profane A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thieſts in a dangerous e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate.</note> that though the day of iudgement may bee further of, then thou ſhalt liue to ſee, yet the day of thy death, may bee neerer then thou art aware of, and as death leaueth thee, ſo ſhall iudgement finde thee,<note place="margin">Eccleſi. 11.3. Heb. 9.24.</note> for as the tree falleth ſo ſhall ſhall it lye, <hi>Eccleſiaſt.</hi> 11. verſ. 3. after death next comes iudgement, <hi>Hebrewes</hi> 9.27. and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:25361:20"/> when a wicked man dieth his hope periſheth,<note place="margin">Prou. 11.7.</note> 
               <hi>Prouerbes</hi> 11. If thou dieſt in thy ſinnes, thou ſhalt be found in thy ſinnes, at the day of iudgement; Impenitent <hi>Cain</hi> died long ſince, and yet the day of iudgement when it commeth, ſhall finde him impenitent ſtill, the like may bee ſaid of <hi>Saul,</hi> of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitephel,</hi> of <hi>Iudas,</hi> they dyed deſperately, and impenitent, and the Lord ſhall finde them ſo at his comming: and ſo will it be with thee whoſoeuer thou art, that goes on in thy ſinnes without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>pentance:<note place="margin">S. Greg. Dialog. lib <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>39.</hi>
               </note> for as Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> teſtifieth <hi>qualis hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>que egreditur, tal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s in iudicio preſentatur,</hi> In what eſtate ſoeuer a man doth d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>part out of this life, in the ſame he ſhal be found at the day of iudgement. And <hi>S. Amb. de bono mortis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Ambroſ. de bono mortis.</note> He that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n this life, doth not receiue remiſſion of ſinnes, ſhall not haue part there, to wit in the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Saints,<note place="margin">S. Hierom. cap. <hi>6.</hi> in Epiſt. ad Galat.</note> in the life to come; And <hi>S. Hierome, Tempus ſementis tempus eſt preſens,</hi> the time of ſowing is the time pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and hee that will not ſowe the ſeede of good workes, in the ſeede time of grace here, hee ſhall neuer reape the fruite of reward in the harueſt of glory hereafter.</p>
            <p>I will cloſe this point with that religious exhortation of Saint <hi>Auguſt.</hi> let euery man while hee hath time,<note place="margin">S. Auſt. lib. <hi>3.</hi> de ſymbolo. Hic dum tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus habet agat anima proſe poenitentia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diu locus eſt miſcricordiae quia ibi erit locus iuſtitiae. <hi>The Second ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cumſtance, the manner of this iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Luk. 17.24. 2. Pet. 3.10.</hi>
               </note> repent truly of his ſinnes, while hee is in the place of mercy, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe then there ſhall bee a time of iuſtice, the fooliſh vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins that would not repent, and prepare themſelues in time, ſhall then receiue no other comfort, but that dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſentence <hi>non noui vos,</hi> I know you not depart from me ye workers of iniquitie.</p>
            <p>And thus from the time, I proceede to the manner of this iudgement by fire, which is the ſecond circumſtance, I obſerued in the fiery colour of the Bowe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As the lightening commeth from the Eaſt and ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vnto the Weſt, ſo ſhall the comming of the Sonne of man be, <hi>Luk.</hi> 17. verſe 24. Hee ſhall come <hi>ex improuiſo,</hi> like a thiefe in the night, ſuddainly; He ſhall come like lighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, viſibly, for euery eye ſhall ſee him; hee ſhall come <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Reuel. 1 7. Mark 13.26 1 Theſſ. 4.16.</note> with power, and great glory, magnificently; to be ſhort, the Lord himſelfe ſhall deſcend from heauen, with the voice of the Archangell and the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:25361:20"/> trumpe of God, But <hi>Quid ſibi vult tubarum ſonus?</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Chryſoſt. Hom. <hi>77.</hi> in Mat. Ad exuſcitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem, ad gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, ad expri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſtuporem, ad dolorem corum qui re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquuntur. <hi>2. No imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the Saints at the day of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> S Auguſt de ciuit dei lib <hi>2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> cap. <hi>15.</hi> S. Auſt lib. de ciuit. <hi>22.</hi> c. <hi>16.</hi> Magiſt ſent. lib. <hi>4.</hi> diſt <hi>44. 3. Mat. 3 13.</hi> Locus ſic expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catur a Lyca permundabit i. e. quotidie a varus tentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onibus munlat in Mat. <hi>4. A queſtion.</hi> S. Auguſt. lib. <hi>20</hi> de ciuit. dei cap <hi>20</hi> Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mo ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men co quo a me cummemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rata ſunt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>din<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eſſe ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ia.</note> to what end is this ſound of the trumpet? ſaith Saint <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> in his 77. <hi>homil.</hi> vpon <hi>Matthew</hi> and he anſwereth the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himſelfe. The Trumpet ſhal then ſound, (and the voice of the Archangel, ſhall then bee heard, for the raiſing vp of the dead, for the ioy of the godly, to expreſſe the ſtupor and terrour of Chriſts comming, and for the griefe, and dolour, of many that ſhall heare it: The dead ſhall then bee raiſed, and the bodies of Gods Saints ſhall then be glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they ſhall riſe in the fulneſſe of the meaſure of Chriſt, in a full and a perfect age, in a fitting and conuenient ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that which is leſſe then is fitting ſhall thence bee ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, from whence the creator knoweth, and that which is more, ſhall bee detracted, The integritie and perfection beeing retained, as Saint <hi>Auguſt.</hi> ſpeaketh in <hi>lib.</hi> 22. of the citie of God, <hi>cap.</hi> 19.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To conclude, Chriſt ſhall come to this firey iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with his fanne in his hand, the fanne of his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, (as before he came with the fanne of his mercy) and hee will thoroughly purge his floore, the floore of his Church, and ſeparate the wheate from the chaffe, the Elect from the reprobate, gathering his wheate, into the bleſſed garner of heauen; but burning the chaffe, with the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenchable fire of hell.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Fire is the colour of the Rainebowe, of which I am now to ſpeake, and fire is the iudgement of which I am now ſpeaking; But concerning this fire the queſtion is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, whether it ſhall bee before the day of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or after. Saint <hi>Auguſt.</hi> ſeemeth to be of opinion that it ſhould be after, for ſpeaking of thoſe things which ſhould come about the time of iudgement, hee ſetteth the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>flagration of the world, and the renouation thereof in the laſt place, and he addeth, <hi>quo ordine haec veniant, magis tu o docebit experientia;</hi> in what order theſe ſhall come, experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence will then teach more perfectly, but, I thinke ſaith he, that they will come in that order, in which I haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed them, and in his 18. <hi>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p,</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Auguſt de ciuit. lib. <hi>20.</hi> cap. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>8.</hi>
               </note> of the ſame booke he ſaith plainly <hi>poſt factum iudicium mundus ardebit,</hi> after the iudge
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:25361:21"/> is done,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſwer. <hi>Aquinas add. quaeſt.</hi> 74. <hi>artic.</hi> 7</note> the world ſhall burne. But wee may rather anſwer with <hi>Aquinas,</hi> and with our later Diuines, that this fire ſhall be before the execution of iudgement: for behold, the Lord will come with fire, and with his charets like a whirlewind, to render his anger with furie, and his rebuke with flames of fire, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 66.15.<note place="margin">Iſaiah 66.15.</note> There ſhall goe a fire be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him,<note place="margin">Pſal. 97.2.</note> and burne vp his enemies on euery ſide, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 67 2 Hee ſhall come with flames of fire, rendring vengeance to them that know not God, 2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.8.<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 1.8</note> This ſhall bee the true manner of his comming, and therefore this fire ſhall appeare at the day of iudgement,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.10</note> before the full execution of that finall ſentence: Or otherwiſe we may reconcile <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> with <hi>Aquinas,</hi> and our later Diuines, and anſwere thus: True it is, there ſhall bee fire before the iudgement, that is, <hi>ignis conflagrationis,</hi> the fire of burning and conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming: and there ſhall be fire after the execution of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that is, <hi>Ignis condemnationis,</hi> the fire of hell, in which the Deuils and damned ſpirits ſhall bee tormented for euer.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2. Anſwer. The fire of hell more horrible then that which ſhall burne the world.</hi> S. Aug. de ciuit Dei. l. <hi>20.</hi> c. <hi>16.</hi> S. Ambr. lib. <hi>7.</hi> in Luc cap. <hi>4,</hi> Damaſcen lib. <hi>4.</hi> fides, cap. <hi>28</hi> Ignis non eſt materialis qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis is apud nos, ſed qualem Deus nouit. Greg. in Iob <hi>2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Aug. lib. de ciuit. cap. <hi>21</hi> Magiſt. Sent. lib. <hi>4.</hi> diſt. <hi>44.</hi> Aquinas add. quaest. <hi>77.</hi> artic. <hi>5.</hi> Anſelmus in Elucidorio. Gregor. in Iob cap. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note>And this likewiſe is prefigured in the fierie colour of the Bowe. But this is more terrible then the former, and that diuers wayes. Firſt, in reſpect of the nature of it, which is ſo ſtrange, that it is knowen perfectly of no man, as Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> affirmeth. Some haue thought this fire to bee incorporeall, and wanting corporall flames, but tormenting the damned after a wonderfull manner: ſo S. <hi>Ambroſe, Damaſcen, Gregorie,</hi> and others. And ſome haue thought it corporeall, as S. <hi>Aug. lib.</hi> 21. <hi>de ciuit. Dei. Gehenna corporeus ignis erit &amp; cruciabit corpora damn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>torum:</hi> Hell fire (ſaith he) ſhall be corporall, and ſhall torment the bodies of the damned; ſo the Maſter of the ſentences, <hi>Aquinas,</hi> and others: yet this fire is infinitely more terrible then our common fire, and more tormenting, for <hi>ardet &amp; non lucet,</hi> it burneth and ſhineth not, ſaith <hi>Anſelmus,</hi> that reuenging flame hath burning in aboundance, but it hath no light, (ſaith <hi>Gregory:</hi> yet <hi>Aquinas</hi> thinkes there ſhall be light ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:25361:21"/> for the damned to behold thoſe things which ſhall torment them, (either in reſpect of the ſight of the body,<note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>vltrix iſla flamma concre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mationem ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet, lumen ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro non habet. Aquinas ad quest</hi> 97. <hi>arti,</hi> 4.</p>
                  <p>Hell fire needs not the fodder of wood Iſaiah. 30.33.</p>
               </note> or the fearefull viſions of the minde.) But howſoeuer, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it ſhall be alwayes darke, with <hi>Gregory,</hi> or haue ſome times a glimmering light, with <hi>Aquinas,</hi> it is of a ſtrange, and terrible nature, for it needs not the fodder of wood to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue it in hell, ſince the breath of the Lord, like a riuer of brimſtone ſhall kindle it, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 30.33. But ſome will obiect that place of the Prophet, Tophet is prepared of old, the nouriſhment thereof is fire and much wood, and therefore it ſeemes there is much wood in hell: to which I anſwer, that much wood is attributed to vnto hell, not that there is any there, but to ſhew that the fire of hell is vnquenchable, being once kindled, by the breath of Gods anger, which addes to the terrour thereof.<note place="margin">S. Greg. lib. <hi>4.</hi> dialog. cap. <hi>42.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Againe it is fearefull in reſpect of the place of it, which is in hell, with the diuells and damned ſpirits,<note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Where hell is thought to be.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>S. Hieronymus in Iona. <hi>2.</hi> Sicut cor in medio est ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malis ita infer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nus in medio terrae perhibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</p>
                  <p>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rtull. lib. de anima cap. <hi>55.</hi> Damaſc. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>29.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Aquinas ad queſt, <hi>97.</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>i. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Luk 16.24.</hi> S. Auguſt. de ciuitater, lib. <hi>21</hi> cap. <hi>10.</hi> verisſed naris modis.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The fire of hell eternall.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> where is vtter darkeneſſe, weeping, and wayling, and gnaſhing of teeth, where they are far remote from the company of the bleſſed Saints, and holy Angels; from all ioy, and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for euer: Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> in his fourth booke of dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues, and 42. chapter, being demaunded of one, where he ſhould beleeue this place of torments was: anſwereth, <hi>dé hac retemerè d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>finire non audeo,</hi> I dare not raſhly define of this matter, ſome haue thought it in ſome part of the earth, ſome vnder the earth, about the center, or in the hollowes of the earth, which is the moſt common opinion: ſo Saint <hi>Hierome,</hi> as the (heart ſaith he) is in the middeſt of a liuing creature, ſo hell is ſaid to be in the middeſt of the earth, and of the ſame opinion was <hi>Turtullian, Damaſcen, Aquinas,</hi> and other diuines, but whereſoeuer it is, certaine it is, that it is a fearefull fire, both in it ſelfe: and the torments thereof: for it ſhall torment both the bodies and ſoules of the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <hi>crucior in hac fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mma,</hi> I am tormented in this flame, was the ſong of rich Diues in hell, and Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> affirmeth that the ſpirits are tormented with that corporeall flame, after a wonderfull manner, but vnvtterable and vnknowne vnto vs: laſt of all it is moſt terrible in reſpect of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:25361:22"/> of it: for as the worme neuer dieth, ſo the fire ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer goeth out,<note place="margin">S. Auguſt. de ciuit. lib. <hi>21.</hi> cap. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Marke</hi> 9.48.<note place="margin">Marke 9 48.</note> and <hi>paria paribus rela<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>nt,</hi> like are referred to like, ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine:</hi> on the one ſide e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall puniſhment, on the other eternall life, according to our Sauiour, <hi>Matthew.</hi> 25.46. And to conclude, it was the iudgement of the deuill, to be caſt into that lake of fire and brimſtone, where the beaſt and falſe prophet are and ſhall be tormented day and night for euermore, <hi>Reu.</hi> 20.10<note place="margin">Reuel. 20.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>And thus hauing ſhewed the time, and manner of this fiery iudgement, I will ſpeake ſomewhat of the end, and vſe of it (to vs) and ſo proceed vnto that which followeth.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, ſeeing all theſe thing muſt bee diſſolued, what manner of perſons ought we to be in all holy conuerſation, and godlineſſe, looking for, and haſting vnto the comming of the day of God, wherein the heauens being on fire, ſhalbe diſſolued,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.11, 12 The fire of ſinne muſt be quenched.</note> and the elements ſhall melt with feruent heat; the conſideration of theſe things ſhould mooue vs to quench in our hearts the fire of ſinne, (whoſe flames doe abundantly burne in the world) that ſo we may be free from this fire of puniſhment. But how many neglect this conſideration, and therefore they burne in the fire of ſinne, and are ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in the flames of iniquitie. The whole world lieth in euill (ſaith S. <hi>Iohn) in maligno,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Iohn 5.19.</note> 
               <hi>quaſi in maloigne:</hi> in euill, that is as it were, in an euill fire, by which they are ſtirred vp to all kind of impieties. They are like to thoſe of whom the wiſe man ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">VViſd. 2.6, 7, 8, 9, &amp;c. The commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> practiſe of the world.</note> 
               <hi>Wiſdome</hi> the ſecond, that call one to another in their ſecuritie, Come, let vs fill our ſelues with coſtly wine and oyntments, and let no flower of the Spring paſſe by vs; let vs crowne our ſelues with roſe buds before they bee withered, let none of vs goe without his part of volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſneſſe, let vs oppreſſe the poore righteous man, and not ſpare the widowe, nor reuerence the ancient gray haires of the aged. Let our ſtrength be the Law of iuſtice; for that which is feeble, is ſaid ſo bee nothing woorth. Thus doe they encourage themſelues in their wickedneſſe, and goe on forwards in their ſinnes,<note place="margin">A deſcription of the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neds co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaint in hell.</note> but what ſhall bee in the ende thereof? The time will come when this deuouring fire ſhall appeare, that their ioy ſhall be turned into ſorrow, and their
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:25361:22"/> mirth into mourning, their Comicall prologue, into a Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall Cataſtrophe, when they ſhall crie out with a dolefull lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tation, what hath pride profited vs?<note place="margin">VViſd. 5.8, 9.</note> or what good hath riches with our vaunting brought vs? for all thoſe things are paſſed away as a ſhadow, and as a poſte that haſted by. They ſhall crie out with terrour and amazedneſſe, woe and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, what a fearefull change doe we behold,<note place="margin">A fearefull change for the wicked.</note> our pleaſures are turned into torments, our riches into extreame pouertie, our delights into woefull puniſhments, our pleaſant ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, into grieuous ſighing: we haue runne blindfolded into this ſcorching lake of fire and brimſtone, our eyes, which our abundance of pleaſures had ſhut vp, are now opened by our abundance of puniſhments. Alas, what doe we behold? there is nothing that can bring vs comfort, but all things that may torment vs; there is no way to eſcape, our caſe is deſperate. O death,<note place="margin">Death deſired of the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but neuer obtained.</note> whom ſometimes wee did tremble to thinke of, come now, and deliuer vs from theſe miſeries: thou, who waſt ſometimes a horrour vnto our guiltie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, bee now a comfort in ſeazing vpon vs. O yee fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of hell, pull yee, rend yee, teare yee in pieces our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happie carkeiſes, and free vs from theſe intollerable do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours. O miſerable wretches that wee are, for how mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarie pleaſures, haue wee procured theſe euerlaſting miſeries? In this manner ſhall the wicked lament their follies, but all in vaine, it will be too late for them then to repent: for it is a time of iudgement, and not of mercie. O beloued, that men would lay lay theſe things to their hearts, and ſet them continually before their eyes, that they might forſake their ſinnes, and eſcape theſe grieuous and dolefull lamentations.</p>
            <p>Againe, ſhall the King of heauen and earth Chriſt Ieſus,<note place="margin">The glorious manner of Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> come to execute this fiery iudgment, with power and great glory? ſhal he come with excellent ſplendor, with admirable beauty? ſhall he come with the bright ſhining weapons of war, to fight with his enemies? ſhal he take to him his ielouſie for complete armour; put on righteouſneſſe for a breſt plate, and true iudgement inſtead of a helmet? ſhall bee ſharpen his ſeuere wrath for a ſword? and ſend out his right aiming
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:25361:23"/> thunderbolts againſt his aduerſaries?<note place="margin">A good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable.</note> O then how happie ſhall that man bee, that hath a peaceable and quiet conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; it ſhall bee better vnto him, then thouſands of golde and ſiluer, yea, then all the riches that are in the world: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe bee ſhall meet his Iudge with ioy, and his King with comfort: For <hi>idem erit Iudex, qui Patronus, qui Mediator, qui Pontifex,</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Ambroſ. lib. <hi>1.</hi> de Iacob. cap <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> ſaith S. <hi>Ambroſe;</hi> the ſame ſhall be our Iudge, who is our Redeemer, our Patron, our Mediatour, our chiefe Prieſt, who hath offered a ſweete ſmelling incenſe of recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation to God his Father for our redemption, and therfore we need not to feare.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">An accuſing conſcience terrible.</note>But how woefull ſhall be the ſtate of accuſing conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the wicked and damned reprobates? O vnhappie wretches! which of you can bee able to meet this deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring fire, theſe euerlaſting burnings? which of you can dare to encounter this inuincible warriour? O miſerable miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creants! prepare yourſelues, for you muſt combate with this commanding Emperor:<note place="margin">Nazianzen in Apologetico.</note> Did you neuer dreame of this bitter conflict in your life time? Woe therefore vnto you now, for ye can neither auoid, nor bee able to endure the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence of his wrath; yee are ouercome already, and bound, and deliuered to eternall captiuitie. For as <hi>Nazianzen</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, <hi>Solus Deus nec faga vitari, nec bello ſuſtiner<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> potest,</hi> onely God this mightie Iudge, can neither bee eſcaped by flight, nor indured in warre, <hi>Extrema illa die, nullum erit effugium, aut perfugium;</hi> in that laſt day there ſhall bee no euaſion or run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning away. True it is, the wicked hypocrites, damned A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts,<note place="margin">Reue. 6.15, 16</note> and ſecure formaliſts, ſhal call and crie to the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines to fall on them, and to the hilles to hide them from him that ſitteth vpon the throne, and from the wrath of the Lambe, but it will not profit them; they ſhall trie all wayes to eſcape,<note place="margin">Greg. Decret. part. <hi>2.</hi> cauſa <hi>11.</hi> quaſt. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> but there is none will helpe them. For although it bee too often ſeene in the world, (as <hi>S. Gregory</hi> obſerueth) that humane iudgement is peruerted, either <hi>timore,</hi> for feare of greatneſſe, by which corrupt iudges are moued, to ſmoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the truth, abſolue the rich, and condemne the poore, or <hi>amore,</hi> for loue and friendſhip, by which the bands of equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie are broken in pieces, or <hi>odio,</hi> for hatred and malice, when
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:25361:23"/> enuy poſſeſſeth the ſoule to deſtruction,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. in hom. inuidia peſtiferum ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum hominem in diaboli con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionem ac in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daemonem im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitisſimum conuertit. Boſkier. defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus neque a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> odio neque timore neque cupiditae te capiendus qua caeteri ſolent. S. Auguſt. de fide ad mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nach. In Chriſti iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio ſine accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſine ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu poteſtatum aqualiter iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicabuntur do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini &amp; ſerui reges &amp; mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, diuites &amp; pauperes humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les &amp; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limes. S. Bern. cap. <hi>11.</hi> ac Rob mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch. <hi>A good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſhall be better then a full purſe. 1. Kings 13.33. Iudges 17.10 Malac. 3.8.</hi>
               </note> or laſt of all and worſt of all <hi>Cupiditate,</hi> for couetouſneſſe, when bribes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert the eies of the wiſe, and mooue them to ſubuert the way of wiſedome, to hearken to the voice of tempting Angels, rather then to the voice of equitie and right, to the voice of a corrupted ſeruant, or bribing oppreſſor, then to the pitifull cry of a poore diſtreſſed plaintiue.</p>
            <p>But this Iudge is incorrupt in his affections, he can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bee mooued by loue, nor by hatred, by feare, nor by bribes, to peruert iudgement, by which the corrupt iudges of the world, are too often mooued, And <hi>S. Auguſt.</hi> excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently <hi>de fide ad monachum;</hi> In the iudgement of Chriſt, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out acception of perſons, or receiuing of bribes) there ſhall be equally iudged, the king and the ſubiect, the maſter and the ſeruant, the rich and the poore, the humble and the proud, euery one ſhall be iudged according to the ſtraight rule of iuſtice, and ballance of equitie; And <hi>S. Bernard</hi> ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>illic plus valebunt pura corda quam aſtuta verba, &amp; conſcientia bona quam marſupia plena,</hi> at that day of iudgement, pure hearts, ſhall be better then craftie words, and a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, better then a full purſe, But in this age of the world it is not ſo, for a full purſe will doe more, then either a pure heart, a good conſcience, or a good cauſe; it will make the corrupt Lawyer, to deceiue his client, the corrupt patron to ſell the liuings of the Church (with which he is only put in truſt) and to place in them <hi>Ieroboams</hi> Prieſts, of the baſeſt of the people, or <hi>Michas</hi> hirelings, that will be content with a few ſhekels of ſiluer and a ſute of apparell, to place igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, ſimonie, and impietie, where he ſhould place learning, honeſtie, and religion, to be briefe, it will make the corrupt magiſtrate, to winke at offences with partialitie, where hee ſhould puniſh with ſeueritie; it cauſeth the ſacrilegious Church robber, to robbe Chriſt Ieſus, in robbing his mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, the oppreſſing Landlord, to ſucke the bloud of his te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, the bribing vſurer, to eate the fleſh of his creditours, the ſophiſticating Tradeſman, to vſe the ballance of deceit and falſe meaſure of iniquitie; And laſt of all it maketh vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſcionable iuror, to ſell his ſoule to the diuell, to forſweare
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:25361:24"/> himſelfe for a bribe, and ouerturne witneſſes, iudges, iuſtice and all. But let all theſe know, that the time ſhall come when this iuſt iudge will finde them out,<note place="margin">Reuel. 22.12.</note> who will render to euery man according to his worke, and giue them their por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with hypocrites, binde them in bonds of darkenes,<note place="margin">Mat. 24.51.</note> and chaines of miſerie for euermore: And this he will do when he ſhall come to pronounce that iuſt iudgement both to the righteous, and the wicked, that twofold iudgement, <hi>iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um approbationis &amp; iudicium reprobationis,</hi> the iudgement of approbation, and the iudgement of reprobation, The firſt in which the righteous are approoued, and rewarded with ioy, the ſecond in which the wicked are reprooued, and rewarded with puniſhment, the firſt in which that bleſſed ſentence ſhall be pronounced to the godly, <hi>venite benedicti</hi> come ye bleſſed of my Father; receiue the kingdome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for you from the foundation of the world. O moſt bleſſed and ioyfull word: <hi>Venite;</hi> come ye, Come from the troubleſome ſea of this world, wherin ye haue beene toſſed, into the quiet Hauen of peace;<note place="margin">A bleſſed change for Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</note> Come from your ſorrowfull warre, vnto ioyfull triumph; Come from exile vnto your country: from your earthly cabbins, vnto caeleſtiall and ſtately palaces; from your poore cotages vnto a kingdome: To conclude, come ye from labour vnto reſt, from miſery vnto ioy, from earth vnto heauen, where ye ſhall inioy pleaſures, without end, treaſures without meaſure, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable glory for euermore,<note place="margin">Better is po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie with a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence then all the pompe and pelfe of the world without <hi>S. Auguſt. in Pſal.</hi> 110. The day of iudgement a ioy to the godly, but ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour to the wicked.</note> 
               <hi>O terque quaterque beati.</hi> O thrice and foure times, nay thouſand times ten thouſand times happie ſhall they be, whom this bleſſed ſentence ſhall embrace, who would not for a little ſpace in this life, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure any miſery, and vndergoe any torments, to keepe faith and a good conſcience, that hee may inioy this bleſſed ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence? with what ioy, and comfort, may the godly expect this ioyfull time, although the wicked cannot thinke of it but with terrour? For as <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaketh. <hi>Iudicum for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midandum malis propter paenam, amandum bonis propter coronam,</hi> This diuine iudgement, it is to be feared of the wicked, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of their puniſhment; but to bee loued of the godly, becauſe of that bleſſed crowne they ſhall then inioy, it
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:25361:24"/> ſhould therefore be ioy vnto Gods children, as it is terrour vnto the wicked. Terrour vnto them becauſe of that feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſentence which ſhall bee pronounced againſt them, in that ſecond iudgement, when Chriſt Ieſus ſhall ſpeake vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, not with a <hi>veni,</hi> come thou bleſſed, but with an <hi>Abi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A fearefull ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration.</note> goe thou curſed, not with an <hi>euge,</hi> well done thou good and faithfull ſeruant, but with an <hi>apage,</hi> away thou wicked and ſloathfull ſeruant, depart into euerlaſting torments, prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the diuell and his angels: O moſt horrible ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thunderclap! O fearefull lightening! woe vnto them,<note place="margin">A horrible thunderclap for the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked.</note> whoſe heads and hearts, ſhall be ſmitten with thy terrour, thou ſendeſt the wicked into tormenting flames, but how many houres, or daies, or monethes, or yeares, ſhall they remaine in that ſcorching fire? their houres cannot bee numbred, their monethes meaſured, nor their yeares deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, their houres are eternall, their yeares eternall, and their fire eternall, for that fire hath no end, into fire they are ſent, and in fire they ſhall bee tormented for euermore. For as the ſhippe beeing oppreſſed, with bellowing waues,<note place="margin">The ſoule of man like a ſhippe.</note> ſinketh downe to the bottome of the ſea, ſo the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, beeing loaden with the fearefull billowes of Gods anger, ſinke downe to the bottome of hell; from whence they ſhall neuer ariſe.</p>
            <p>The Marriners that carried <hi>Ionah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ionah 1.5.</note> fearing the danger of the ſea, call forth their goods and lightened their ſhippe, now the ſoule of man, is as it were a little ſhippe, toſſed too and fro, in the troubleſome ſea of this world, and bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heauie loaden, with the grieuous weight of ſinne, is almoſt euery moment, readie to ſuffer ſhipwracke;<note place="margin">Beware of ſhipwracke.</note> O beloued ſeeing then the euerlaſting flouds of Gods an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, which ſhall ouerflow the damned in hell, are ſo hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible and vnſufferable; how willingly ſhould wee caſt out all things that may endanger this weake, craſie, and leaking ſhippe of our ſoules; (be they neuer ſo deare vnto vs,) rather then incurre this eternall, and moſt fearefull ſhipwracke, how willingly ſhould we caſt out the in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>llerable burden of our ſinnes, and drowne them in the ſea of repentance, that our ſhippe may bee
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:25361:25"/> lightened, and made free from this terrible danger. Thus we ſhould doe, and thus if we doe, happy and bleſſed ſhall wee be, we ſhall be ſafe from the floods of Gods anger, &amp; flames of his vengeance, and be imbraced in the armes of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. Which mercies, hauing now paſſed theſe two great and terrible iudgements of water, and of fire, noted in the two firſt colours of the Rainebowe, the colour of water, and the colour of fire commeth in the next place to bee ſpoken of.</p>
            <p>The grace and mercie of God, by which hee preſerueth the world from that future deſtruction, noted in the greene and gracious colour, ſignifying the ſpring of Gods fauours, and the ſummer of his mercies; <hi>I haue ſet my Bow in the cloud, and it ſhall bee for a ſigne of the Couenant betweene mee and the earth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>The greene colour noting the mercy of God, by which he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth the world from deſtruction.</hi> Ferus in Gen. cap. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Paraeus in Gen. cap. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Iuſtitiae quide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quod olim mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus propter im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietatem, aqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum diluuio iuſte deletus ſit vt Deum ſimili profanitate of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendere metua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus miſericor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diae vero quod &amp;c vt ad amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem &amp; grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinem erga Deum exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lament. 3.22</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> 
               <hi>Diſcamus ex Iride non iuſtitiae noſtrae eſſe quod mundus non iterum deletus fuit, aut deleatur, ſed diuinae miſericordiae,</hi> ſaith a good Interpreter; We may learne from the Rainebow, that it is not of our righteouſneſſe, that the world hath not been deſtroyed, or is not now brought to deſtruction, but of the grace and mercy of God, figured in the greene and gracious colour of the Bowe: and a later writer agreeing with the former, obſerueth the ſame point after this manner, <hi>Ex ſigno foederis diuinitus nobis propoſito, iuſtitiae pariter, &amp; miſericordiae recordemur;</hi> from the ſigne of the Couenant, propoſed vnto vs from God, wee are put in minde, both of his iuſtice and mercie; of his iuſtice, in that hee deſtroyed the world with a deluge of waters, to teach vs that we ſhould feare to offend him with the like prophaneneſſe.</p>
            <p>But of his mercy in that hee doth not deſtroy the world a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, to mooue vs to ſhew our loue and thankefulneſſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him for the ſame. It is of the Lords mercy, that wee are not conſumed, becauſe his compaſſions faile not, <hi>Lamen.</hi> 3.22. For the mercy of the Lord is like a riuer of water, flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing throughout all nations, watering all generations, and abounding throughout all ages: the mercy of the Lord is like the ſea, compaſſing the earth, on euery part, the mercy of the Lord is like the Sunne, ſhinning both vpon the good and bad, vpon the iuſt, and vniuſt, it hideth it ſelfe from
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:25361:25"/> none, but giueth preſeruation vnto all: it lifteth the wicked from the mire of iniquity, and directeth the godly in the waies of piety, it giueth all good things both temporall and eternall: health, beauty, honours, riches, and ſtrength; and therfore I may conclude with the Prophet <hi>Dauid, Pſal.</hi> 103. The mercy of the Lord is from euerlaſting, to euerlaſting,<note place="margin">Pſal. 103.17.19.</note> vpon them that feare him, and his righteouſneſſe vnto childrens children, the Lord hath prepared his ſeate in heauen, and his kingdoms ruleth ouer all, gouerning all things by his mighty power, and conſeruing them by his continual preſence, And therefore for this end, according to that olde rule in diuinity, <hi>Enter, praeſenter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Polan ſyntag.</note> 
               <hi>Deus hic &amp; vbi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> potenter,</hi> God is here, and God is euery where by his eſſence, by his preſence, and by his power: and S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> pithily vpon the 6. of Matthew, God is in himſelfe,<note place="margin">S. Auguſt ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per illua Mat. <hi>6</hi> pater noſter. <hi>&amp;c</hi> Deus eſt in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſo ſicut α &amp; ω in mundo ſicut rector &amp; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, Angelis ſicut ſapor &amp; decor, in eccleſiae ſicut pater fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milias in domo, in animo ſicut ſponſus in thae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamo, in iuſtis ſicut adiutor &amp; protector, in r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>probis ſicut pauor et terror</note> as the <hi>Alpha,</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> the beginning, and the ending, he is in the world, as the rector, and author, he is in the angels, as the ſweete ſauour and ſplendour; hee is in the Church, as the Father of the Family in the houſe; he is in the ſoule, as the bridegroome in the bride-chamber; hee is in the godly, as their helper, and protector; and in the wicked, as their feare, and terrour. But by his mercifull prouidence, hee is gratious vnto all, hee layeth the beames of his chambers, in the waters, and maketh the clouds his charriots, and wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vpon the wings of the winde; hee watereth the hills from his chambers, and the earth is filled with the fruite of his workes, he cauſeth the graſſe to grow for the cattell, and greene hearbs, for the ſeruice of men; hee hath appointed the Moone for certaine ſeaſons, and the Sunne knoweth his going downe. O Lord our God how manifold are thy workes, in wiſdome haſt thou made them all, the earth is full of thy riches: thus doth God daily manifeſt his fauours to the whole world, in keeping it from deſtruction, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing all good things for the preſeruation of the ſame. But the cauſe of this loue, is the free grace and mercy of God, <hi>gratia dei dat homini vitam &amp; motum,</hi> (ſaith a learned writer) the grace of God doth giue to man, both life and motion:<note place="margin">Barrardius Tom. <hi>2.</hi> lib. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> and what is this world without the water of grace? truely
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:25361:26"/> nothing but a dead ſea, or ſodomicall lake, in which nothing can liue.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Chriſt the Arke of grace Iohn 1.14. Coloſſ. 2.3.</note>Of this grace Chriſt Ieſus is the Arke wherein it is kept for vs, who was figured by the Arke of the teſtament, who is full of grace and truth, and in whom are hidden all the treaſures of the wiſedome and knowledge of God. This grace is <hi>aqua Christi,</hi> the water of Chriſt, with which is his loue, he doth ſprinkle the ſoules of his ſeruants: it is <hi>aqua A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>elorum,</hi> the water of Angels, with the taſte of which they are refreſhed, as with the riuers of the waters of life, it is <hi>aqua Hominum,</hi> the water of men, by which they are che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, as with the liuing fountaine of Gods fauours: it is <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>qua omnium,</hi> the water of all things, by which they are preſerued in the loue and fauour of their gratious Creator: to be ſhort, this water of grace floweth from God, floweth vnto God, and aſcendeth towards heauen, yea it bringeth men vnto God, and into heauen.</p>
            <p>Thus haue I ſhewed you the grace of God in generall, let me ſpeake ſomewhat of it in particular: hee hath beene gratious vnto the whole world, in preſeruing it,<note place="margin">A deſcription of the grace of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward England</note> and hath beene gratious vnto this land, in preſeruing vs. O England thou haſt taſted in abundance, of the riuers of Gods grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous fauours, thou haſt beene made rich with his loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens; thou haſt beene deckt with the ornaments of his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, he hath put a chaine about thy necke, bracelets on thy hands, and frontlets on thy browes; he hath clothed thee with broydered worke, and ſhed thee with Badgers skinnes, he hath girded thee about with fine linnen, and couered thee with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ilke, he hath made thee glorious with ſiluer, and gold, thou doſt eate fine flower, hony, and oyle, thou art exceeding beautifull, and art proſpered into a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, thy renowne is gone forth amongſt the nations, for thy beauty, for thou art made perfect, through the comlineſſe which thy God hath put vpon thee: his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies are great vnto thee, for hee deliuered thee from thy enemies on euery ſide, both at home and abroad, both ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill and forraigne: from the terrible <hi>Armado</hi> of the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, in eighty eight, from that horrible powder plot of the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:25361:26"/> Papiſts, with many other villanous treaſons in latter daies; of which thou mayeſt ſay with the land of Iſrael, if the Lord himſelfe had not beene on our ſide,<note place="margin">Pſal. 134.2, 3, 4.</note> (may England now ſay) when men roſe vp againſt vs, they had ſwallowed vs vp quicke, when they were ſo wrathfully diſpleaſed at vs, the waters had drowned vs, and the ſtreame had gone o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer our ſoules: but bleſſed be the Lord, who hath not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs ouer as a prey vnto their teeth; the Lord hath deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered thee from the ſword, from the famine, and from the peſtilence; peace is within thy walles, and plenteouſneſſe within thy palaces, he hath filled thee with the flower of wheate, and embraced thee with mercy and louing kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. O beloued vnſpeakeable are the bleſſings,<note place="margin">The bleſſings of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable.</note> and infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite are the graces which he hath manifeſted vnto vs; hee hath giuen vs a gratious King, a wiſe, learned, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding <hi>Salomon,</hi> whom God of his mercy long preſerue amongſt vs, he hath giuen vs a royall Queene, and a hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full progenie, for the continuance of his fauours, whom God of his mercy long preſerue amongſt vs; hee hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs a worthy, carefull, and vigilant Counſell, with a wiſe Nobility, a reuerend Clergie, learned and religious Arch-biſhops, and Biſhops, conſcionable, graue and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Iudges: all which, God of his mercy, long preſerue amongſt vs; to be ſhort, he hath giuen vs famous vniuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties for the ſupply of our wants, either in Church or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, and for the encreaſe of learning, and religion, which God to the encreaſe of his glory long preſerue amongſt vs. And laſt of all, which paralels all the reſt, (for had we not that, we had nothing) he hath giuen vs the rich treaſures of his glorious Goſpell for the ſaluation of our ſoules: which God of his vnſpeakeable mercy long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue amongſt vs, and let euery true hearted Chriſtian ſay <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus hath God manifeſted his mercy to our whole land: But once againe let mee turne vnto you, yee religious and worthy Citizens, and tell you what God hath done for your ſoules: Infinite are the graces that God in his mercy hath beſtowed vpon you, I cannot number them; he hath giuen
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:25361:27"/> you religious, zealous, and worthy Senatours, diſcreet and wiſe Magiſtrates, vnder our Royall <hi>Moſes,</hi> to carry the ſword, and to goe in and out before you with comfort; and this grace be continueth vnto you ſtill;<note place="margin">The Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from all p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ts of the kingdome, their incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rageme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>red by wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s. Anno 1603. there died within &amp; with out Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>don of all diſeaſes, 38244. of the plague, 30578</note> hee hath giuen you riches, and treaſures in great abundance, he hath giuen you that moſt precious iewell of his bleſſed word, after an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent manner: what countrey, what nation, what citie in the world doth inioy a more ioyfull ſupply of learned, zealous, and worthy Preachers continued vnto them after a more worthy order, then this famous Auditorie?</p>
            <p>God did looke vpon you with an angrie countenance, whipping you with a rod of correction for your ſinnes, when of late dayes, there died in one yeare aboue thirtie thouſand amongſt you, in that great and generall plague. But now he looketh vpon you with a fauourable eye, and hath freed you from that fearefull iudgement, which free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome God of his infinite mercie long preſerue amongſt you. And I may ſay of all theſe mercies, to the whole world,<note place="margin">The grace of God the cauſe of all graces toward vs.</note> to this land, and to this citie, that <hi>Gratia Dei est cauſa, author, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffector omnis gratiae:</hi> the grace of God (figured in this gracious colour of the Bowe) is the cauſe, authour, and effect of all grace, fauour, and mercy towards vs. For if we demaund the queſtion, what is the cauſe that God did create all things for our good, before hee created vs? The Anſwere muſt bee <hi>Gratia Dei,</hi> the free grace and mercie of God. What is the cauſe that hee hath not ſpared his owne Sonne, but giuen him to the death for our redemption? <hi>Gratia Dei,</hi> the free grace and mercy of God. What is the cauſe that hee hath giuen vs a gracious King, vnder whom we enioy the peace of the Goſpell, the meanes of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation? <hi>Gratia Dei,</hi> the free grace and mercie of God. In a word, goe throughout all the graces that God hath beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon vs, and demaund the queſtion of euery one, why hath God done thus? And the anſwere muſt bee, <hi>Quia bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Thankfulnes, that which God requires for h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings.</note> Becauſe he is good and gracious, and becauſe his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie endureth for euer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quid retribuemus Domino?</hi> What then ſhal we render vnto the Lord, for his this vnſpeakeable mercie, and moſt infinite
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:25361:27"/> grace? Wherewith ſhall wee come before the Lord, and bow our ſelues before the moſt high God? Shall wee come before him with thouſands of rammes, or with tenne thouſand riuers of oyle? Shall wee giue our firſt borne for our tranſgreſſions, the fruite of our bodies for the ſinnes of our ſoules, to pay for our ingratitude, and to recompence that loue which God in his mercy hath ſhewed vnto vs? No, no, Beloued; this is not that which God requireth at our handes: it is Thankefulneſſe, to loue mercie, to doe iuſtly, and to humble our ſelues, to walke with our God;<note place="margin">Micah 6.6, 7.8.</note> we ſhould take the cup of ſaluation, and call vpon the Name of the Lord; wee ſhould pay our vowes now in the preſence of all his people; wee ſhould offer vnto him the ſacrifice of thankſgiuing, and tell out his workes with gladneſſe. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinely ſaith S. <hi>Bernard,</hi> Happie is that man,<note place="margin">S. Bern. Serm. contra ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinem. Foelix quid ad ſingula dona gratiae redit ad ad eum in quo est plentitudo omnium gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiarum.</note> who for euery gift of grace, returneth vnto God, in whom is the fulneſſe of all graces whatſoeuer. O then let vs giue thankes vnto the Lord, becauſe hee is gracious, and his mercie endureth for euer: Let Iſrael now confeſſe, that hee is gracious, and that his mercie endureth for euer: Let the houſe of <hi>Aaron</hi> now confeſſe, that his mercie endureth for euer: Let the people of England now confeſſe, that his mercie endureth for euer. And laſt of all, let all they that feare the Lord, continually confeſſe, that his mercie endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth for euer.</p>
            <p>This thankfulneſſe God requireth at our hands, and this we are bound to render vnto him; But doe we thus?</p>
            <p>Surely, the vineyard of the Lord of hoſtes,<note place="margin">Iſaiah 5.1, 2, 3, &amp;c.</note> is the houſe of England, and the men of England are his pleaſant plant, he hath manifeſted his loue vnto them, hee hath taken care for them, he hath fenced them with a wall of peace, he hath gathered the ſtones from them, ſo that nothing might hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their fruitfulneſſe, he hath planted them with the choi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſt vine, the vine of his word, hee hath built a tower in the middeſt of them, the tower of his graces, hee hath made a winepreſſe therein, prepared all things for their good; what could he haue done more vnto his vineyard, that he hath not done vnto it? now he looked that we ſhould bring
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:25361:28"/> forth grapes, but haue we not brought forth wilde grapes? he looked for thankfulneſſe, may I not ſay behold ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude? he looked for iudgement, may I not ſay behold op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion? he looked for righteouſneſſe, may I not ſay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold a crye? If I ſhould ſay it of all, I ſhould condemne the innocent, but I may ſay it ſoone of too many, and iuſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue the nocent. There is a crie that is heard in our land, but it is not a crye of thoſe that ſhout for the maſtery, nor of thoſe that lament for being ouercome, nor of thoſe that ſing and make melody, theſe might bee paſſed ouer: but it is a crye of ſinne, a cry of iniquity, that aſcendeth vp into the eares of the Lord, from the ſeuerall and ſecret corners of the land.<note place="margin">The crying tinnes of our ſime.</note> Should I bring you a Catalogue of theſe ſinnes, it would weary mee to ſpeake them, and weary you to heare them, or at leaſt to heare of them: I will therefore but touch ſome of the principall, I know not where to begin, but Pride, ſteps forth and challengeth the firſt place.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Pride.</note>There is a crye of Pride, of horrible Pride, men are trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed into women, and women into men, ſuch is their ſtrange Metamorphoſis and prepoſterous order that one ſtriueth to goe before the other in Pride. It ſeemeth ſome of them haue ſearched the Scripture, be it but to ſearch out ſinnes, that they may immitate them: for whereas the Lord by the Prophet reprooueth the abhominable pride of the daughters of Sion, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 3. their haughtineſſe, their ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched out neckes,<note place="margin">Eſay. 3.16.</note> their wanton eyes, their walking and min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing as they goe, making a tinckling with their feete, their tinckling ornaments, their caules the round tyres like the Moone, and the like, the ſonnes and daughters of our Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on haue learned to goe beyond them, and to outſtrip them in pride, painting their faces, and painting their cloaths, in ſuch a deformed manner, defacing their naturall formes, that at the day of iudgement God will not know them to be his. But againſt theſe, the Lord threatneth a fearefull puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 3.24. It ſhall come to paſſe, that in ſtead of ſweet ſmell, there ſhall be ſtinke, in ſtead of a girdle, a rent, in ſtead of well ſet hayre, baldneſſe, and burning, in ſtead of beauty. And I would to God this City were free from this
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:25361:28"/> ſinne, that it might be free from this puniſhment.</p>
            <p>After this, a ſecond iniquitie rideth poſt, and now whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome walketh hand in hand with pride, and ſometimes iuſtles for the wall, there is a crye of whoredome,<note place="margin">2. Whordome</note> yea it is growne to ſuch a height, that now many of our gallants, account it but recreation,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>3. Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Iſaiah <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>8.1. 3. Mothers. 3. Daughters 4 Oppreſſion Iſaiah 5.8. Iſaiah 3.15. 5. Simony.</hi> Quatuor eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias portes intra tur in omnes, C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſaris &amp; Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moni, ſanguinis atque dei. Prima patet magnis numis paetet altera, charis Tertia. ſed pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis quarta pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere ſolet. S Greg in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ab. <hi>1.</hi> queſt <hi>1.</hi> cum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s au <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>tia id <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rum ſit ſeruitus, quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (&amp; ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>in dan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>) r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> infideli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>is pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioniſubijci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r etia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tdum ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d neque fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ijs vid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atur</note> and our prophane Atheiſts will boaſt of their bawdery.</p>
            <p>Drunkenneſſe begins to quarrell, and is angry that her daughter whoredome is preferred before her; but I anſwer her greeting, rayling with the Prophet, Woe to the crowne of pride and drunkenneſſe of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> and woe vnto them that riſe vp early to follow drunkenneſſe, and continue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till night, till the wine doe inflame them. And (ob) that this City were free from theſe ſinnes, that it might be free from theſe woes: but theſe are three vicious mothers, that bring forth three venemous daughters oppreſſion, ſimmony, and ſacriledge; which like the leane Kine of Egypt, denoure all they meete with.</p>
            <p>Hence commeth the crye oppreſſion, worſe then the crye of the children of Iſrael, againſt their Taske-maſters in Egypt, the poore labourer cryeth for vengeance againſt the Depopulator, and the hunger ſtarued tennant, againſt the rent-racking landlord. But woe bee vnto them that ioyne houſe to houſe, and lay field to field, till there bee no place that they may be placed by themſelues in the midſt of the earth: and woe vnto them that grinde the faces of the poore (ſaith the Lord or hoaſts.</p>
            <p>Simony is ſiſter to Oppreſſion, for when the field is depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulated, corne groweth ſcarce and therefore the oppreſſing Patron muſt part ſtakes with the Simonicall incumbant, for eaſe of charge, hence it commeth to paſſe that of thoſe foure ordinary gates of entrance into the Church, <hi>Caeſaris &amp; Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſanguinis atque dei,</hi> By fauour of Caeſar, of Simony, of Friends, and of God, three of them are almoſt ſtopt vp, and their paſſages growne ouer with graſſe, but the path of Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony is made a high way, becauſe ſhee hath played the ingroſſer, and bought the Monopoly of the reſt.</p>
            <p>Sacriledge is fellow heire with Simony, and goeth to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:25361:29"/> law with religion,<note place="margin">Non vndecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tollere hoc est ſacrilegium committere, ſed de Eccleſia qui aliquid futatur Iudae proditori, comparatur.</note> for the right of the Church, and it is to be feared without the mercy of God, and fauour of the King, that in many places they will be quite ouerthrowne, witnes that abhominable crye of horrible Sacriledge, that foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in the world, where the godleſſe depopulators haue incloſed fields, townes, Churches and all, pulling thoſe downe, which their religious fore-fathers did build vp, ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping their doores with thornes, and their windowes with buſhes, yea couering their roofes with thatch, nay leauing them naked, or els turning theſe holy places into barnes, or ſheepe coates, or other prophane vſes, ſo that for lacke of people, the earth and bruite beaſts may complaine to the Lord,<note place="margin">Pſal. 79.1.</note> in the words of the Prophet, O God, the heathen are come into thine inheritance, thy holy Temple haue they defiled, and made Ieruſalem an heape of ſtones: many more are the crying ſinnes of theſe daies, but two eſpecially had deed to be ſpoken of, the firſt is Hypocriſie and diſſimulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the ſecond Schiſme and diuiſion.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">7. Hypocriſie.</note>There is a crye of hypocriſie euery where to bee heard, for how many are there that profeſſe themſelues to be the ſeruants of Chriſt, and yet when occaſion ſerues, will haue concord with Beliall, and ſerue the diuell; that will make a ſhew of offering ſacrifice vnto God, in the temple of the Lord, and yet ioyne themſelues with Idolatours in the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of idols, that will ſerue the Lord at Ieruſalem, and yet offer oblations to the golden calues in Bethel, and in Dan: that will beſure to verifie the prouerbe, Run with the Hare, and yet hold with the Hound; profeſſe ſimplicitie with the Sheepe, and yet practiſe their ſubtiltie with the Foxes, play on both hands, like <hi>Ambo-dexters,</hi> fit, and frame, and faſhion themſelues for all companies, with the religious, they will ſeeme religious, and with the prophane they wil follow pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe; with the godly they will ſeeme to be godly, and with the wicked they will practiſe iniquitie; with the ſober they will commend ſobrietie, but yet they will not ceaſe to bee drunke with the drunken; with the continent they will extoll chaſtitie, they will not refraine the harlots houſes to commit adultery. To bee ſhort, they are like Ferrie-men,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:25361:29"/> looking one way, but rowing another way, bearing men in hand, that they are trauelling forwards, in the narrow way that leadeth vnto life, when indeede they are walking for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in that broad path that leadeth to deſtruction: for what kinde of wickedneſſe, will they not commit, being intized vnto it, by the deceitfull baits of profit, and pleaſure, ſabbath breaking, ſacriledge, ſimonie, vſury, periury, vilanie,<note place="margin">Stony ground Math. 13.21.</note> and what not; making ſhipwracke of faith, and of a good conſcience, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh. But ſuch as thoſe are, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue their ſeede amongſt ſtones, and therefore hindring the roote of the word, by their ſtony hearts, they obtaine only the leaues of profeſſion, and are altogether depriued of the good fruite, of a true religion, their faith is reſiſted, by the ſtones of error, their hope reſiſted, by the waues of feare, and their charitie reſiſted, by the bluſtering windes of malice and enuy, they are compoſed of inconſtancy, and therfore wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the firme and ſtable pillars of faith, hope, and charitie, their houſe of hypocriſie, is ſuddainly ouerturned, by that ſtrong man, the diuell, (more mightie then <hi>Sampſon</hi>) &amp; they themſelues, with their outſide profeſſion, beaten to peeces in a moment.</p>
            <p>The laſt ſinne is ſchiſme, and diuiſion in the Church,<note place="margin">8. Schiſme.</note> and the cry of this is ſo grieuous, that it grieues me to thinke of it, much more to ſpeak of it, moſt of all to behold it amongſt our ſelues, In the primitiue Church,<note place="margin">Acts 2 46.</note> they were all of one minde, and all of one heart, O happie vnion! O bleſſed time! but now how many minds, how many ſchiſmes? how many diuiſions in the Church? and that many times about ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, about ceremonies, about circumſtances, while let the ſubſtance goe, one ſaith I am of <hi>Paul,</hi> another I am of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llo,</hi> another I am of <hi>Cephas,</hi> another I am of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is Chriſt diuided? did <hi>Paul</hi> die for you? or was <hi>Apollo</hi> crucified? cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it is, that you cannot diuide Chriſt, though you may diuide our ſelues from Chriſt; O then take heede, of ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Chriſts ſeameleſſe coate, of making Schiſme,<note place="margin">Chriſt ſeame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te muſt not bee rent.</note> and diuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Church, labour to keepe vnitie, with veritie, and veritie, with vnitie, leaſt Chriſt caſt ye forth of the Church, take his coate of protectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you, &amp; ſo being found naked, in the ſtormes of miſery, ye periſh in the day of vengeance.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:25361:30"/>
            <p>Thus (right Honorable, and beloued,) from this greene and gratious colour of the Bow, I haue ſhewed you the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God, by which he preſerueth the world from deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I haue ſhewed you the infinite graces, which he hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vpon this land, vpon this citie, I haue ſhewed you the vnthankefulneſſe of many in the world, manifeſted in the crying ſinnes of the time,<note place="margin">S. Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſoſt. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m <hi>2.</hi> ad p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pulum Antioch. ſic incipit.</note> of which I may conclude as S. <hi>Chryſostome</hi> begins his ſecond Homily to the people of Antioch, <hi>Quid dicam? aut quid loquar? lachrymaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> preſens tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus, non verborum, &amp;c.</hi> What ſhould I ſay? or what ſhould I ſpeake? it is a time of teares, and not of words, of mourning, and not of ſpeaking, of prayer, and not of preaching ſuch is the mag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de of ſin, the vncurable wound of iniquitie, &amp; vniuerſall plague of impiety, that it is impoſſible to be hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led without the powerfull hand of a mightie God. That of <hi>S. Auguſt.</hi> now verified;<note place="margin">S. Aug lib. <hi>4.</hi> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Baptiſm. con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a Donat. Infidelis diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat contra fide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſed improbus Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſtianus vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit contra fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vn le cum v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> aduceſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ei neuter per illam potest habere ſalute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> The vnbeleeuing Pagan, diſputeth againſt faith, and the wicked Chriſtian liueth againſt faith, from whence it commeth to paſſe, that ſince both of them are aduerſaries vnto faith, neither of them can haue ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by faith. True it is, beloued, that the Lord hath freed vs from h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s iudgements, and giuen vs peace, by which wee inioy the comfort of the Goſpel; but let vs take heed, leſt by our ſins we mooue him to remooue our candleſtick, to depriue vs of our peace, and ſend his terrible plagues amongſt vs. O that theſe crying ſinnes were baniſhed our land, then happy and bleſſed ſhould we be! I know there is not wanting religious and zealous Biſhops, graue &amp; worthy Iudges, who are care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and vigillant, to baniſh theſe hatefull cries both from Church and Common wealth. But ſuch is the ſubtilty of the ſerpent, and corruptions of the times, that this crie is either ſtopped before it commeth to their eares, or elſe the ſinnes themſelues (like painted harlots) are ſo masked, and gilded ouer with the colors of deceit, that their vgly countenances cannot be ſeene,<note place="margin">Poteſtetiam appluarie illud S. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n. Oportet humiliter de ſe ſentire nitente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad altiora, &amp;c. in Cant. ſer. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> &amp; by this meanes they eſcape vnpuniſhed.</p>
            <p>If I my ſelfe were in place, to ſpeake vnto thoſe which are in authoritie, I ſhould conſider my owne vnworthineſſe, and confeſſe with S. <hi>Bernard, non eſt meae humilitatis dictare vobis,</hi> It is not for my humilitie (Right honourable lords) to dictate vnto you, or to tell you what you ſhould doe, I
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:25361:30"/> know ye are wiſe, ye are zealous, ye are religious. But yet my duty to my great Lord, and maſter, my loue, to his Church my mother, and my earneſt deſire, for the good, and welfare of my King, and country, binds me as it bindeth all, continually to pray vnto that great Lord Keeper of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, to defend his glory, his Church, our King, and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and to beate downe theſe crying ſinnes, that ſo wee may inioy our gratious peace, with his bleſſed graces for euermore; and I hope there is none but will ſay, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you haue heard theſe three principall colours of the Rainebowe, the colour of water, the colour of fire,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The three colours note the Trinitie.</hi> S. Baſilius mag. in Epiſt. Perſonatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietates velut flos quidam ex illis qui appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de in vnoquo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geam, nec vllu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſe ipſorum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſe differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam ſecundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> naturae propie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem. ſed in communitate ſubſtantiae diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criminis propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etates in vno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lucere.</note> and the greene colour, the ſigne of grace, (with their three principall morals) at large declared vnto you; yet once againe, S. <hi>Baſil.</hi> the great who was <hi>magni nominis in Eccleſia,</hi> of great name in the Church of God, excellently obſerueth further, that this heauenly Bowe, doth by a fit ſimilitude, in his threefold colour, reſemble vnto vs that holy and bleſſed Trinitie; For as in the Bowe there is a threefold colour, and yet but one Bowe, ſo in the glorious Trinitie, there are three perſons, and yet but one and the ſame eſſence: And as theſe colours are ſo mingled, and knit togither in the Bowe, that we cannot diſcerne, where one is ſeparated, or diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed from the other; ſo is it in the diuine eſſence, the perſons be diſtinct in themſelues, yet can wee not finde out (by our humane wiſedome) in the proprieties of their natures, the ſeparation of one from the other; for as in the Rainebow all the colours are one, in communitie of the ſame ſubſtance; ſo in the Trinitie, all the perſons and the glory of them, is one, in the indiuiſible communitie of the ſame eſſence;<note place="margin">Hugo de Prato Florido. Dimin. Sanct. Trinitat. Serm. <hi>1.</hi> Nihil eſt in v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſo mun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tam inuiſibile &amp; incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſibile, ſicut vnitas, &amp; Trinitas.</note> And this reaſon by the creature, doeth teach vs, that wee ſhould take heede that we conceiue not any vaine opinion of this heauenly doctrine, when beeing drawne into any difficult place, wee doe diuerſly turne our ſelues, to reconcile thoſe things which are ſpoken; for as in theſe things which are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed to the eye, experience is better to teach the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the cauſe it ſelfe; ſo likewiſe in thoſe high points, and miſteries of diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, faith is better, and more auaileable, then all the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of reaſon, in the world.</p>
            <p>Laſt of all Tropologically, theſe three colours of the Bow,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:25361:31"/> may ſignifie thoſe three Theologicall graces,<note place="margin">The three co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours note, Faith, Hope, and Charitie. <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>gas Ribeta, Per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rius in Apocal.</hi>
               </note> Faith, Hope, and Charitie: the caerulean colour, Faith, the greene colour, Hope, and the red, Charitie: which graces, the diuine Rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowe, that is the grace of God, doth ſhowre downe in abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance vpon his ſeruants, as diuers Interpreters well obſerue. Theſe are the three principal colours of the Bow: and from theſe and diuers others, ariſing from the reflection of theſe there doeth appeare an excellent beauty, in the admirable Rainbow. I meane not now to diſpute thoſe many queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,<note place="margin">Diuers que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions about the colours.</note> concerning theſe colours, which are diſcuſſed by anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and moderne Philoſopbers, as whether theſe colours of the Rainbow be colors according to the veritie of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or in appearance only? whether that which lieth between the leſſer periferie, or circumference of the Bow, &amp; the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, be a thing coloured or not? whether that which is ſeene between the two Rainbowes (the principall and that which is cauſed by refl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xe of the principall) bee coloured with the purple, carnation, and fiery colour? whether the light in the middle be any qualitie? and in a word, whether it be poſſible that a third Rainbowe ſhould appeare, and for what cauſe? with diuers others of the like curioſitie. I will not now ſtand to diſpute the cauſes of theſe ſeuerall colours, or the diuers reaſons of each one in particular, becauſe it doeth more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to Philoſophy, then diuinitie, neither will I now proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute any further the diuers morals of theſe different colours.<note place="margin">The third part. The ſituation of the Raine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow in the cloud. <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rcer. in Gen.</hi>
               </note> But rather haſten to the next part of my text, the ſituation of the Bow, in the cloud (of which with the reſt) I wil ſpeak but briefly, and ſo draw towards a concluſion. <hi>I haue ſet, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mercerus</hi> in his Commentary vpon <hi>Gen.</hi> hath noted out of <hi>Raſian</hi> Hebrew, that when God ſpake vnto <hi>Noah,</hi> he made the Rainbow then to appeare in the cloud, and as pointing vnto it with his finger, ſaith thus, <hi>Ecce, hoc eſt ſignu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſoederis &amp; arcus qeum vides;</hi> behold, this is the ſigne of the couenant, and the bowe which thou ſeeſt, we haue no certaine warrant for this opinion.<note place="margin">Ferus in Gen.</note> But certaine it is, that <hi>hoc ſignum non in terra, ſed in coelo conſtituit,</hi> God did not place this Bowe in the earth, or in the ſea, but in the heauen, that it might be ſeene of all, and he cauſeth it to appeare <hi>tempore plunioſo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">God offereth grace to all.</note> in the time of raine: To teach vs firſt, that God offereth the ſignes of his grace
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:25361:31"/> vnto all, &amp; therfore al ſhould take notice of them, &amp; remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber his loue; if they neglect this, they are made without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe. 2. That God is more powerfull then his creatures,<note place="margin">God more powerfull the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. In miſerie God remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth mercy.</note> he can keepe them from hurting his ſeruants, ſeeme they neuer ſo prepared, and therfore we need not be afraid of the ſignes of heauen, or terror of the clouds. Thirdly, &amp; laſtly, to teach vs, that in midſt of miſery, God remembers mercy, for when the clouds ſhowre downe raine, as if they would drowne the world, euen then God ſheweth his Bowe, the ſigne of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, for the comfort of his ſeruants. Againe,<note place="margin">Allegorie 1.</note> the ſituation this Bow is in the cloudes: but yet the ends of it doe reach downe to the earth;<note place="margin">Ariſt. Sect. <hi>13.</hi> Problem. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> &amp; in the time of <hi>Ariſt.</hi> it was the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon opinion, that the Rainbow lighting with her two ends vpon the hearbs &amp; flowers, did make them much more ſweet and odoriferous: concerning which, how &amp; when it is done, he diſputeth at large in his <hi>Problems.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plinius lib. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> But <hi>Pliny</hi> doth conſtantly affirme, that the tree <hi>Aſpalathus,</hi> the roſe of Ieruſalem, or our Ladies roſe, by the touching of the rainebow, is made much more delectable. And as the rainbow doth giue an excellent odor to all herbs,<note place="margin">Plinius lib. <hi>17.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> ſo ſpecially it doth giue to this an vnuttera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſweetnes, for when the earth is watered, &amp; the Rainbow doth cſt down her ſeed vpon it, ſhe doth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſend forth that diuine &amp; heauenly breath, to which no ſweetnes can be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared. Which notable effect of the rainbow,<note place="margin">Ariſtale hist. animal lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ariſt.</hi> deſcribeth further, teaching, that to the generation of that <hi>melaeris,</hi> that hony of the aire (which our Philoſophers called <hi>mel roris,</hi> the hony of deaw, &amp; we the hony fall) the Rainbow doth giue a principal furtherance. But I faile too long in this Philoſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal ſea; yet of this there is not wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting a Theological vſe.<note place="margin">Allegory 2. As the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h make ſw et the flowe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the earth, ſo Chriſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the ſight of God. Math. 3.17.</note> For as the rainebow with her heauenly deaw, diſtilling from the clouds, doeth giue an excellent odour, to the flowers of the earth vpon which it doth light; ſo likewiſe Chriſt Ieſus, who is that myſticall Rainbow &amp; eternall ſigne of Gods fauour, with the caeleſtiall dew of his ſpirituall graces diſtilling from the throne of his mercy, (which is perfumed with the ſweet ſmelling incenſe of his meritorious ſacrifice) doeth ſweeten with melliferous odours, the hearts, and ſoules and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of his children, making them acceptable in the noſtrils of their heauenly Father.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:25361:32"/>
            <p>And therefore at the ſight of this beautifull Bowe, we may remember with vnſpeakable ioy, that moſt bleſſed, and ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Bainebowe, the Sonne of God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Allegorie 3. <hi>Arist. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Meteorolog. viſade longe apparent mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranigriora.</hi> The further we are from Chriſt, the leſſe of his glory can wee behold. Iſa. 59.2.</note>Thirdly, the ſituation of this Bowe is in the cloudes, and the further we are from it, the leſſe beautifull glorious, and delectable, it doth appeare; and ſo likewiſe the further wee are from Chriſt Ieſus, by our naturall corruption, impeniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and continuance in ſin, the leſſe glorious, beautifull, and excellent doth he appeare vnto vs; but the neerer we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach vnto him, by faith, holineſſe, and newneſſe of life, the more glorious ſhall we behold him, and more earneſtly long to inioy him; O then beloued! how ſhould wee labour, with the bright flames of zeale, to baniſh the darke clouds of our ſinnes, which do make a ſeparation betweene Chriſt and vs; and obſcure the light of our eies, that we cannot behold, the brightneſſe of his glory; How earneſtly ſhould we ſtriue, to draw neere vnto him; that being refreſhed at the ſight of his beauty, we may behold with ioy, &amp; comfort, ſo glorious a Rainebowe, and being confirmed in faith, we may one day inioy his bleſſed glory for euermore.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Allegorie 4.</note>Fourthly, the Rainebowe is placed in the clouds, but by how much the Sun is higher, by ſo much this Bow is leſſer: for at the middle of the day,<note place="margin">The more grace beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon vs, the more hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of vs.</note> it is thinner, ſmaller, &amp; narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er (although of a greater circle:) And ſo likewiſe by how much higher Chriſt Ieſus, who is the Sunne of righteouſnes, is in our hearts, that is, by how much the more he doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre his giftes and graces vpon vs; by ſo much the more ſhould we labour to beate downe our naturall pride, and bee leſſer in our owne conceits: for by this meanes it will come to paſſe, that howſoeuer wee may ſeeme vile in the ſight of the world, yet ſhall wee bee accounted honourable in the ſight of God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Allegorie 5.</note>Fiftly, the Rainebowe being in the cloude, ſeemeth grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the ſunne, which men may meruaile at, becauſe it is but the glaſſe of the Sunne, ſhewing the image therof, the Sunne being the obiect, and cauſe of the Bowe; But the reaſon is, becauſe the Bowe is a glaſſe of this nature, that it doth make the obiect much greater, and doth increaſe the formes into a wonderfull magnitude.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:25361:32"/>
            <p>And herein thoſe doe paralel the Bow,<note place="margin">Vile ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude. Mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of their owne honor, but forgetfull of Gods.</note> who receiuing all that they haue from God, as the Rainebow doth receiue her light and glory from the beames of the Sun; yet labour to extoll their owns glory, aboue the glory of their maker: ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king greater care, for their owne honour, then for the glory and honour of God, who in this will be like the Rainebow, though not in any thing they ſhould: like thoſe who as the Bow appeareth onely in the day, and not in the night, ſo likewiſe immitating the Bowe,<note place="margin">Diſſembling Chriſtians.</note> they will make profeſſion of Chriſt in the day time of proſperity, but when the night of aduerſitie approcheth, they forſake their profeſſion, &amp; leaue Chriſt to himſelfe, rather then they will endure the leaſt miſerie for his ſake; or like thoſe who as the Bow hath both endes downewards,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Os homini ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime dedit.</hi> But couerous wordlings like bruite beaſts looke euer downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</note> ſo they bend all their affections down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, caſting their eyes vpon the ground, ſearching greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the mucke and pelfe, and vaine honours of the world, but ſeldome or neuer lifting vp their hearts or eyes towards heauen, to ſeeke for the riches and treaſures thereof. But we muſt not ſo immitate the Bow, but as (according to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of the ancient) the Rainebow letting downe her hornes vpon the earth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Virgil.</hi> 1. <hi>Greg. Plaut. Curcul. &amp; Propertius lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cleg</hi> 4. <hi>Vitrunius lib.</hi> 9. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. Looke down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vpon Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, and ſend vpward thy thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, then will God ſend down his graces vpon thee.</note> doth draw vp the water from the fountaines to the cloudes, which being turned into ſhowers, doe returne and water the fruites of the earth, for which cauſe this phraſe was vſed of them <hi>arcus bibit aquas</hi> the Bow doth drinke vp the waters, (which opinion <hi>Vitrunius</hi> defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, calling the Bow a notable inſtrument by which God doth draw vp the waters from the earth, into the ayre, by this meanes to make the ground more fruitfull: ſo likewiſe beeing inlightened with the heauenly brightneſſe of Gods gracious Spirit, and caſting downe both our eyes to behold the infinite bleſſings of God vpon the earth; we ſhould be mooued by diuine contemplation, to ſend vp the ſweete ſmelling vapours of thankefull hearts, towards the cloudes of heauen, that being conuerted into the diuine ſhowers of Gods mercifull fauours, we may be made fruitfull, with all ſpirituall graces whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>To conclude the Rainebow doth appeare in the cloude,<note place="margin">How long the Rainbow ſhall continue</note> But there is a queſtion demanded, concerning the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of it, how long ſhal it remaine &amp; be ſeene in the clouds?
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:25361:33"/> It is reported that ſome holy men were of opinion,<note place="margin">Author Hiſtor. Scholaſt. in lib. Geneſ. cap. <hi>38.</hi>
               </note> that for fortie yeares, before the day of iudgement, and generall bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the world, there ſhould be neither Raine, nor Raine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowe to be ſeene: But what theſe holy men were, I cannot reade, for I can finde none of the ancient Fathers vpon my Text, to be of this iudgement, yet it ſeemeth the ground, and foundation, of this opinion was, that they ſuppoſed that generall burning of the world, could not be effected with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an vnſpeakable precedent drineſſe of the aire, and an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaſurable abundance, of drie exhalations, and ſo much of this drie matter, as they dreamed neceſſarie, for the burning of the world, could not be gathered but in a long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of time, not poſſibly in leſſe then in forty yeares, and therefore for that time, there ſhould be neither Raine nor Rainebowe; But in this reaſon, that which is taken for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, is not only vncertaine, but moſt plainly falſe, for that burning of the world, ſhall not be effected by natural cauſes, but by the ſupernaturall worke, and diuine power of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, as the firſt iudgement was, when the whole world (except <hi>Noah</hi> and his family) was deſtroyed with the floud; And therefore there it no reaſon, why there ſhould not be both Raine,<note place="margin">Petitio principii</note> and Rainebowe, till the day of iudgment, for both theſe ſhall paſſe away with the cloudes, and not before. And thus from the cloudes the ſcituation, I paſſe to the vſe of the Bow, <hi>It ſhall be for a ſigne: I haue ſet my Bow in the cloud,</hi>
               <note place="margin">4. Part. it ſhall be for a ſigne. <hi>Authore Socrat. apud Platonem.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and it ſhall be for a ſigne of the Couenant betweene mee and the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Iris</hi> or Rainebow, is deriued <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of the greeke verbe, which ſignifieth to ſpeake, becauſe it is a ſpeaking ſigne or viſible word, for it is <hi>ſignum pluuiae tum praeteritae, tum inſtantis,</hi> a ſigne both of raine that is paſt, and of raine that is at hand; and therefore it was feigned of the heathen poets, to be <hi>nuncius Iunonis,</hi> the meſſenger of Iuno, and of others it was called <hi>Daemonis (hoc est ſapientis) arcus</hi> the Bow of God, or of a wiſe Creator, becauſe it is a ſigne of the diuine wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, certaine it is that it is <hi>nuncius dei,</hi> the meſſenger of God, by which he doth teſtifie that he will no more bring a generall floud to deſtroy the world.<note place="margin">Two ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of the Bow.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This Rainebow hath two principall ſignifications. In the firſt
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:25361:33"/> one Phiſicall or naturall, the ſecond metaphiſicall or ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall. In the firſt it is <hi>ſignum pluniae,</hi> a ſigne of raine, in the ſecond it is <hi>ſignum ſerenitatis,</hi> a ſigne of faire weather, and this is aboue nature, for all naturall Philoſophy is ignorant of it, onely the Church doth vnderſtand it by faith, out of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueiled will of God, that as often as the Bow doth appeare in the cloud, we remember the couenant and promiſe of God, that the world ſhould neuer againe be deſtroyed with water.</p>
            <p>But how can this be, may ſome man obiect?<note place="margin">Whether the Rainbow was before the flood.</note> how is it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that the Rainebow ſhould be a ſigne, that there ſhould not follow a generall floud, to deſtroy the world, ſeeing the Rainebow was before the floud, and then was no true ſigne of this, as the euent did plainly teſtifie; To this ſome haue anſwered, that the Rainebowe was not before the floud, ſo Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome, Alcuinus,</hi> and the interlinearie Gloſſe.</p>
            <p>But without queſtion this Rainebowe was before the floud, although after the floud, it was appointed for a ſigne.<note place="margin">S. Chryſoſt. Hom. <hi>28.</hi> Gen.</note> Firſt becauſe God did ceaſe from all the workes of creation the ſeauenth day,<note place="margin">Gen. 2.2.</note> ſo that hee did not after create any new ſpecies, or kindes of creatures: and therefore, it muſt needes follow, that the Rainebow was created before the floud.<note place="margin">Pererius in Gen. Quarſum enim Deus hunc e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>inem toto eo tempere impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſer? quorſum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a diuturno mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculo naturale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is ac plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiae generatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prohibuiſſet. Certe nulla ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio reddipotest, cur Deus omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa naturali via refrigerandi terras, pec im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es tanto mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculo exunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium terreſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um aquarum tandiu vti voluit.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, God created the cauſes of the Bowe before the floud, for there was not wanting the cloudes, nor the Sunne, nor a place where the cloudes might be ſet againſt the Sun, vpon which the Sun ſhining, the Rainebowe doth appeare, And therefore ſince the cauſes of the Bowe were before the floud; it muſt needs follow, that the effect of theſe cauſes, the Rainebow, was before the floud alſo, (except it can bee ſhewed, that the generation of the Bowe, was hindred by ſome other impediment, which cannot be) for it is a rule in Philoſophie, <hi>Poſita cauſa ponitur effectus,</hi> the cauſe being pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced &amp; perfected, the effect muſt of neceſſity follow; as when the Sunne draweth towards our Horiſon, the light and day begins to appeare; when the fire is kindled, the heate doth ſuddenly increaſe, or when as a man beholdeth his naturall face in a glaſſe, his image is preſently repreſented to his ſight, ſo likewiſe a ſoone as the ſunne did caſt his bright beames, vpon the glaſſe of the waterie cloudes, the effect thereof, did preſently manifeſt it ſelfe vnto the world, but
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:25361:34"/> this was before the floud, and therefore the Rainebowe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the floud alſo.</p>
            <p>Yet againſt this thoſe of the contrarie opinion, obiect the words of my Text, that God ſpeaketh here vnto <hi>Noah</hi> in the future tenſe, <hi>I will ſet my Bow in the cloude,</hi> &amp; therfore it ſhould ſeeme rather,<note place="margin">Cornelius cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelii a lapide in Comment in Geneſ.</note> that the Rainebow was created after the floud, then before, To which I anſwer, that howſoeuer in the Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuagint tranſlation it is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>pono,</hi> I do put, and in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Latine, <hi>ponam,</hi> I will put, yet (as a learned interpreter well obſerueth) in the Hebrew text, it is in the preterperfect tenſe, NATATTI, <hi>dedi, poſui,</hi> I haue giuen, I haue ſet, and God might well haue ſaid, I doe giue, I doe ſet, or I will ſet, but not that it was not there before, but that it ſhould now bee for a ſigne, of that couenant, betweene me and the earth, for after the ſame manner the water in Baptiſme, was inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Chriſt our Sauiour, to be a ſigne in the ſacrament, and yet water was an element created at the beginning, as the Rainbow was created before the floud, ſo that I may thus anſwer the 1. Obiection, Almightie God, not naturally, but by his diuine inſtitution, hath appointed the Rainebow for a ſigne, that there ſhould not any more come, a generall floud, to deſtroy the world.</p>
            <p>Againe, if the Rainebowe be not a naturall ſigne, of a fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing floud, of what then is it a naturall ſigne of Raine? or of faire weather? of windes? or of the tranquilitie of the heauens? <hi>Plinie</hi> in his ſecond booke of naturall hiſtorie, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to be of opinion,<note place="margin">Plinius lib <hi>2.</hi> natural. hiſt. cap. <hi>59.</hi> Plin lib. <hi>18.</hi> cap. <hi>59.</hi>
               </note> that it is no certaine ſigne of of any of theſe; yet in his eighteenth booke he affirmeth, that when two Rainebowes appeare, it is a ſigne of Raine, and if a Rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowe appeare after ſhowers, it is a ſigne of faire whether, although not alwaies certaine, But <hi>Seneca</hi> teacheth, that as the Rainbow doth appeare,<note place="margin">Seneca. lib. <hi>1.</hi> naturel. queſt. cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> in a diuerſe region of the aire, or in a diuerſe time of the day, ſo it doth portend, diuers things: If in the morning, it ſheweth Raine that is paſt, and ſome ſmall ſhowers to come; If at noone, or there abouts, it is a ſigne of greater ſhowers;<note place="margin">Scaliger. contra cardanum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercitat.</note> but if it appeare at night, it ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth faire weather, to whom <hi>Scaliger,</hi> others accord. And the reaſon of this, is giuen by Philſophers, becauſe a morning Bow, being ful of the moyſt vapours of the night, is
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:25361:34"/> as it were a veſſell, of ſome following ſhowers, by reaſon of the thicke miſtes that remaine. A meridian Bowe, doth carry grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſtore of waters, and portendeth more Raine, becauſe the waters gathered, cannot be dried vp, with the moſt vehement heate of the Sunne, ſuch is the greatneſſe of their force, And an euening Bow, hauing the greateſt part of the moyſt &amp; vapou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry miſte dried vp in the former part of the day, promiſeth faire weather, and therfore ſeldome or neuer doth any ſtore of Raine follow im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ediately after. But I proceede forwards, God hath appointed it for a ſigne.</p>
            <p>And a ſigne as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> deſcribeth it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>S. Auguſt. l.</hi> 2. <hi>de Doct. Chriſt. cap.</hi> 1. <hi>Signum vero eſt res praeter ſpeciem quam ingerit ſenſibus aliud aliquid ex ſefaciens in cogitationem venire.</hi> 2. King. 20.11 Ioel. 2.31. Gen. 2.9. Iudges 6.37, 38, 39. Iſaiah 7.14. Gen. 17.10. Exod. 12.3. Math. 28.19. Luk. 22.19.</note> is a thing which doth cauſe, another matter to be remembred, beſides that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall figure, which it doth ſhew to the outward ſenſes: And ſignes are commonly of 3. ſorts, the firſt, <hi>ſignaſtuporis,</hi> ſignes of wonder and amazement, as the Sun, when it went ten degrees backe at the praier of <hi>Ezechia.</hi> The ſecond <hi>ſignaterroris,</hi> ſignes of terrour and affrightment, as thoſe ſignes which ſhall be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the day of iudgement, when the Sun ſhall be turned into darkneſſe, &amp; the moone into bloud, The third are <hi>ſigna amoris</hi> ſignes of loue and contentment, As the particular ſignes of Gods loue to his elect, and theſe either to certaine perſons, as the tree of life to our firſt parents in Paradiſe, <hi>Gene.</hi> 2. The wet &amp; dry fleece to <hi>Gidion,</hi> or the conception of the virgin to king <hi>Achas,</hi> or to the whole Church either before Chriſt, as Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, the Paſſeouer, &amp; Sacrifices; or ſince Chriſt, as Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, &amp; the Supper, or laſt of all that vniuerſall ſigne of Gods loue, to the whole world, the admirable Rainebowe, which he hath appointed for a ſigne of the couenant, betweene him and the earth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ecce poſt policitationem verbo factam &amp; hoc ſignum addo</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi>) as ſpeaking of God, Behold, after my promiſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> S. Chryſoſtom. Hom. <hi>28.</hi> in Geneſ.</note> I doe giue you a ſeale of my promiſe, to confirme the ſame. So that God doth not only manifeſt his loue by Oracles, and binde himſelfe by promiſe, and couenant, but he proceedeth further, and addes ſacraments, &amp; ſeales to his couenant,<note place="margin">Gods omits nothing that may confirme the faith of his choſen.</note> that he might ſeeme to omit nothing, which might ſerue to confirme the faith of his choſen, Thus did he in the Spirituall couenant, hee gaue to our firſt parents in paradiſe, the ſacrament of the tree of life, and of the tree of knowledge of good and euill, he gaue
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:25361:35"/> to the Patriarches the ſacrament of circumciſion, &amp; the paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, he hath giuen to his church ſince, the Sacrament of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and the Supper: and thus he doth in the corporall coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, he giueth vnto <hi>Noah</hi> the admirable Rainebow, for the confirmation of his faith, and to be a ſeale of the couenant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene him and the earth: to teach vs to baniſh incredulity,<note place="margin">Incredulitie muſt be bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</note> &amp; to beleeue his promiſes. For as the vſe of the Rainebow on the part of God, is to teſtifie his grace and mercy vnto men, ſo the vſe of the Rainebow one the part men, is to confirme their faith,<note place="margin">Mercelus in Geneſ.</note> and loue towards God, the Iewes are exceeding religious in this matter, for when they ſee the Rainbow, they go forth, fall downe, and confeſſe their ſins, acknowledging themſelues worthy to bee drowned with a floud of Gods vengeance; though we are not bound to be ſuperſtitious, yet fitting it is, that we ſhould not forget Gods infinite loue, and mercy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Allegorie 1. The rainbow a ſigne of the Goſpel.</note>Againe it ſhall be for a ſigne, Allegorically this Rainebow is a ſigne of the euangelicall Law, for as the Rainebow being ſet for a ſigne, did ſhew forth peace, pardon, and glory, ſo the euangelicall law, brought with it, grace, remiſſion of ſinnes, and promiſe and aſſurance, of eternall glory in the heauens. Secondly this Rainebow doth ſignifie the incarnate word of God,<note place="margin">Allegorie 2.</note> God in the fleſh, or the humanity of Chriſt, and that after a manifold analogy,<note place="margin">A manifold Analogie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Chriſt and the Bowe.</note> and ſimilitude betweene them For firſt as the Sunne ſhining in the Cloud, doth beget a glorious and beautifull Bow, ſo the eternall word of God, that moſt power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Sunne of righteouſneſſe ſhining in, and vpon our humane nature, did as it were beget a glorious and bleſſed Redeemer, after a diuine and wonderfull manner. Secondly, as the rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow was a Symbole of peace in the time of <hi>Noah;</hi> ſo the incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Chriſt was the reconciliation of the world. Thirdly, the two hornes or ends of the Bowe, may ſignifie the two na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of Chriſt, his diuine, and humane, of which the hidden and inuiſible ſtring, is like vnto the ſecret and admirable hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtaticall vnion of his two-fold nature. Fourthly, in the Rainebowe there is a three-folde colour, and ſo likewiſe in Chriſt; for Chriſt was Caerulean, or Caeleſtiall by prayer, hee was greene and flouriſhing, by the flowers of ſpirituall graces, and heauenly vertues, of which hee was full, as Saint
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:25361:35"/> 
               <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeaketh. <hi>Iohn</hi> 1. <hi>verſe</hi> 14.<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.14.</note> And hee was redde by his bloud, ſhedde vpon the Altar of the croſſe, by treading the winepreſſe of Gods wrath alone, by which his raiment was ſtained, as the Prophet ſpeaketh.<note place="margin">Iſaiah. 63.3.</note> Fiftly as from this Bowe are ſent forth, diuerſe ſecret, ſweete, and comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vertues, amiable to the flowers of the earth, ſo likewiſe, from that myſticall, and heauenly Rainebow Chriſt Ieſus, are ſent downe many ſweete, comfortable, and hidden arrowes of diuine loue, with which his bleſſed ſpouſe, being wounded to the heart, ſings in her paſſionate loue to Chriſt her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, ſtay me with flagons, comfort me with apples, for I am ſicke of loue. Sixtly, as this Bowe is <hi>imbrifera,</hi> a Rainie-bowe,<note place="margin">Cant. 2.4.</note> ſo likewiſe was that diuine Rainebow Chriſt Ieſus, when one the day of Pentecoſt, he did ſhower downe in abundance, the ſweete raine of heauenly grace, and caeleſtiall doctrine, into the hearts of his Apoſtles, &amp; doth continually ſhower downe, his infinite bleſſings vpon his ſeruants. In a word this Raine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow being a ſemicircle deſcending towards the earth, and aſcending towards heauen, may fitly ſhew Chriſt deſcending towards the earth to take our nature vpon him, to free vs by his paſſion from the wrath of his father, and his aſcenſion to prepares a place for vs, where we ſhall one day liue, and reioyce with him, in glory and happineſſe, for euermore. And thus doth the Rainebowe figure that heauenly Bowe Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            <p>Or otherwiſe this Rainebow is a figure of Chriſt,<note place="margin">In another manner the Rainebow is a figure of Chriſt.</note> the clouds may ſignifie his body, the threefold colour, his three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold ſubſtance, his fleſh, his ſoule, and his diuinitie, or his threefold ſupreame dignity, ſpoken of by the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> of King, of Iudge, and of Lawgiuer, or laſt of all, his threefold ſpirituall office, of King, Prieſt, and of Prophet.<note place="margin">Per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rius in Geneſ.</note> To be ſhort the Philoſophers teach that the Rainebow doth conſiſt of a threefold ſubſtance, the earth, the water, and the aire, from whence doth ariſe the threefold varietie, of his colour, of greene, redde and watery; And by this is inſinuated the greatneſſe, of diuine mercy,<note place="margin">Gods mercy in a threefold reſpect.</note> manifeſted vnto men in a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold reſpect, in the ſtate of nature, of the law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and of the Goſpell: in the ſtate of creation, of naturall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and ſpirituall grace: in the grace of predeſtination,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:25361:36"/> from all eternitie, of iuſtification in time, and of glorification, beyond all time. But I dwell too long in theſe Allegories; yet once againe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It ſhalbe for a ſigne.</hi> We reade in the Scripture of diuers ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paritions of this glorious Bow, in the viſion of the diuine ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie,<note place="margin">Ezek. 1.28.</note> which was ſhewed to <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> the brightneſſe of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God was like vnto the Bow that is in the cloud in the day of raine. In the Reuelation to that Euangelicall Prophet S. <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel. 4.3.</hi> Polan. de Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramento fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deris.</note> there was a rainbowe round about the throne, in ſight like vnto an Emerald: A Rainebowe, to ſignifie that God was mindfull of his couenant with <hi>Noah,</hi> and with his poſteritie. In ſight like vnto an Emerald, to ſhew the mercy of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the penitent, whom God doeth refreſh with a gracious countenance.<note place="margin">Pererius in Geneſ.</note> A Rainbow compaſſing a throne: the Raine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow ſignifieth the mercy of God, and the throne his Church, to ſhew, that God doeth protect and defend his Church with perpetuall mercy, as the Rainbow did compaſſe the throne.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, in another viſion, S. <hi>Iohn</hi> beholdeth a mightie Angell come downe from heauen,<note place="margin">Reuel. 10.1. Angel. Chriſt, Cloude, Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie, Rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowe, Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</note> cloathed with a cloud, and a raine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow vpon his head, his face ſhining like the Sunne, and his feet as pillars of braſſe. A mightie Angel, that is Chriſt Ieſus clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with a cloud, that is, his humanitie; and hauing a Raine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow about his head, to ſhew that he is the Author of the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and of our reconciliation with God, figured likewiſe by the Rainbow in my text. But I paſſe to the laſt part of my text, the intimation of the internall ſignificate, in the laſt words, <hi>Of the couenant betweene me and the earth:</hi> Of which I will giue a touch, and ſo conclude.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The fift part. Couenant.</note>
               <hi>Erit ſignum foederis,</hi> it ſhalbe for a ſigne of the couenant; that is, a ſigne which ſhall ſeale, and confirme that couenant which I haue entred with mankind, as the ſeale of a King confirmeth the Charter granted to his ſubiects, nay much more firme, for that may altar, becauſe it is from man, but this is vnchangea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,<note place="margin">A twofold Couenant.</note> becauſe it is from God. This Couenant which God hath entred with mankind, is twofold, a ſpirituall couenant, and a corporall couenant: The ſpirituall couenant doth conſiſt of two branches, the firſt, the couenant of works, and the ſecond, the couenant of grace.<note place="margin">Couenant of workes.</note> The couenant of works, is that which God made with our firſt parents, before their fall, promiſing
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:25361:36"/> vnto them eternall happineſſe, if they continued obedient vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his commandements, which were dictated vnto them, as by word of mouth, and written in their hearts, by the power of his Spirit. The current of this was, <hi>Hoc fac, &amp; viues,</hi> doe this, and thou ſhalt liue.</p>
            <p>The couenant of grace<note place="margin">Couenant of grace.</note> was that which God made with our firſt parents, after their fall, promiſing them eternall life, and freedome from wrath in Chriſt Ieſus, the ſeede of the woman ſhall breake the head of the ſerpents. <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">Geneſ. 3.15.</note> The current of this is, <hi>hoc crede &amp; viues,</hi> Beleeue this and thou ſhalt liue.</p>
            <p>The corporall couenant,<note place="margin">Corporall co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant.</note> concerneth temporall benefits; and this is that which God made with <hi>Noah,</hi> and his ſonnes, and their poſterity for euer, and with euery liuing creature, vpon the face of the earth, eſpecially aymed at by <hi>Moſes,</hi> in the wordes of my text, <hi>It ſhall bee for a ſigne of the Couenant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene me and the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. This couenant was made betweene God and the earth, that is the inhabitants of the earth, with <hi>Noah</hi> and with his ſeede after him. God then was mindfull of vs, before we were borne,<note place="margin">God mindfull of vs before wee were borne.</note> mindefull of vs not in anger, but in grace, much more will be not be forgetfull now, while we walke in the path of faith, and waies of righteouſneſſe. 2.<note place="margin">The mercie of God farre exceeds his iuſtice.</note> Againe this couenant was an euerlaſting couenant, not to continue for a ſhort time, but to the end of the world, to ſhew that the mercy of God doth farre exceed his iuſtice, for the rigour of his iuſtice, was but for a little ſpace, in once deſtroying the world by water, but his mercy is perpetuall, in the continuall preſeruation thereof. For a moment in mine anger, haue I hid my face from thee, but with euerlaſting mercy haue I had compaſſion on thee, (ſaith the Lord of hoaſts) <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 54 8.<note place="margin">Iſaiah 4.8.</note> To mooue vs to relye on Gods mercy, in the depth of miſery, and to ſing with the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> Sorrow may indure for a night,<note place="margin">Pſal. 30.5.</note> but ioy commeth in the morning.</p>
            <p>To conclude,<note place="margin">The ſpirituall couenant, the fountaine of the corporall.</note> 
               <hi>it ſhall be for a ſigne of the couenant betweene mee and the earth.</hi> Of this couenant the Rainbow was a ſeale, and as it ſealeth this couenant, ſo it ſignes in this that eternall co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant of God with his Church,<note place="margin">Ferus in Geneſ.</note> which is the fountaine and foundation of this; <hi>Pactum hoc cum Noe praefigurauit faedus Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti cum Eccleſia,</hi> ſaith one: This couenant with <hi>Noah</hi> did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figure
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:25361:37"/> that couenant of Chriſt with his Church, ſpoken of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 54.10.<note place="margin">Iſaiah 54.10.</note> 
               <hi>Iris deſignat Chriſtum, qui eſt ſignum reconciliationis perfectae.</hi> The Rainbow doeth figure Chriſt, who is a figure of our perfect reconciliation, a ſigne of our eternall friendſhip with God the Father, and an euerlaſting memoriall of our peace:<note place="margin">Chriſt the myſticall rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow an euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall of our peace.</note> For although the Rainebowe, the outward ſigne, ſhall paſſe away with clouds; yet notwithſtanding, the couenant, of which it is a ſigne, the memorial of our redemption, that ſhall remaine for euer in the ſight of God the Father, and be viſible in the fleſh of his Sonne, in the charactars of the wounds of his hands, of his feete, and of his ſide, by which hee procured our moſt happie and endleſſe peace;<note place="margin">Rom. 5.1. Actes 10.36. Epheſ. 1.6. Hebr. 1.14. Iſaiah 11.6. Acts 4.32. Luke 2.29. Phil. 4.7. Ecclus. 2.14.</note> peace with God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yea with the bleſſed Trinitie, peace with the bleſſed and glorious Angels, bleſſed and happy peace one Chriſtian with another. And laſt of all, but not leaſt of all, peace of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which paſſeth all vnderſtanding. Which happy and endleſſe peace with God the Father, with the bleſſed Trinitie, the glorious Angels, the bleſſed Saints, and our owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, with euerlaſting bleſſedneſſe for euer, God of thy end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe mercie, and moſt infinite grace graunt vnto vs, to thy whole Church, to euery one of thy faithfull ſeruants, for the vnſpeakeable loue, and ineſtimable merits of thy deare Sonne, our bleſſed Sauiour: To whom with thee and the holy and moſt bleſſed Spirit, one God in Trinitie, and Trinitie in Vnitie, be aſcribed all honour, glorie, and power, all might, maieſtie, and dominion, this day, and for euermore. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:25361:37"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
